<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<sect1 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1"
 xml:id="source-publish">
 <title>Source Publisher</title>
 <para>The job of the source publish service is to publish all sources for 
directly before published binaries. This will include the sources of repackaged
binaries. For example, the sources of RPMs which are used inside of product, 
appliance or container images. A prerequisite for this is that OBS has enabled
content tracking for the used projects.</para>

 <sect2 xml:id="source-publish-configuration">
  <title>Configuring Source Publisher</title>
  <para>The source publishing can be configured via the file
    <emphasis>/usr/lib/obs/server/BSConfig.pm</emphasis>, where it can be 
    enabled globally or just for some projects. It is possible to use regular
   expressions here.</para>
  <para>Publishing can be enabled by defining the rsync module to push the content:</para>
  <screen language="perl">our $sourcepublish_sync = 'rsync://your_rsync_server/rsync_module'; </screen>
  <para>By default every project get published, but it is possible to define a whitelist via:</para>
  <screen language="perl">our $sourcepublish_filter = [ "openSUSE:.*", "SUSE:.*" ]; </screen>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="source-publish-considerations">
  <title>Considerations</title>
  <para>The source publishing service is publishing the sources as they are hosted in &obs;. This
        means these are the unprocessed sources and the content is not identical to the
        content of source RPMs for example. Instead these are the sources which are the
        base for source RPMs.</para>
  <para>As a consequence hints like NoSource: tags in spec files are ignored. The only
        way to disable publishing for the user is to disable access or sourceaccess via
        the flags.</para>
  <para>The filesystem structure is <emphasis>$project/$package/$srcmd5/</emphasis>. A  <xref linkend="obs-glos-disturl"/>
        inside of binary builds can be used to find the right sources.</para>
  <para>&obs; will care for de-duplication on the rsync server. This must get implemented there.</para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
