<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC
  "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<section id="_obs_spider_identification">
 <title>Spider Identification</title>
 <para>
   OBS identifies spiders by using an extension called <command>voight_kampff</command>. Spiders will be identified to hide certain
   content and links for performance reasons.
 </para>
 <para>
   To update the spider list, you must run the command <command>bundle exec rake voight_kampf:import_user_agents</command> in the
   root directory of your OBS instance. This downloads an updated list of user agents as a JSON file into the
   <filename>config/</filename> directory of the Rails application.
 </para>
 <para>
   If you want to extend or edit this list, switch to the <filename>config/</filename> directory and open the
   <filename>crawler-user-agents.json</filename> file with the editor of your choice. The content can look like this:

   <screen>[
   {
       "pattern": "Googlebot\\/",
       "url": "http://www.google.com/bot.html"
   },
   {
       "pattern": "Googlebot-Mobile"
   },
   {
       "pattern": "Googlebot-Image"
   },
   [...]
]</screen>
 </para>
 <para>
  To add a new bot to this list, a pattern must be defined. This is required to identify a bot. Almost all bots have their
  own user agent that they're sending to a web server to identify them. For example, the user agent of the Googlebot looks
  like this:
  <screen>Mozilla/5.0 (compatible; Googlebot/2.1; +http://www.google.com/bot.html)</screen>
  To choose the pattern for the new bot, compare the user agent of the bot you want to identify with others and look for a
  part that is unique (like in the Googlebot example, the part: Googlebot).
 </para>
 <para>
  Let's assume we want to add the bot Geekobot to the list of bots and the user agent looks like this:
  <screen>Mozilla/5.0 (compatible; Geekobot/2.1; +https://www.opensuse.org)</screen>
  Our unique part would be Geekobot. So we add a new entry to the list of bots:
  <screen>[
   {
       "pattern": "Googlebot\\/",
       "url": "http://www.google.com/bot.html"
   },
   {
       "pattern": "Googlebot-Mobile"
   },
   {
       "pattern": "Googlebot-Image"
   },
   [...]
   {
       "pattern": "Geekobot"
   }
]</screen>
 </para>
 <note>
  <para>You can also use regular expressions in the pattern element.</para>
 </note>
 <para>
  Save the file and restart the Rails application and the bot Geekobot should be identified properly.
 </para>
</section>
