<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.1" xml:id="cha-obs-product-building"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" >
 <title>Building Products</title>
 <info/>
 <para> OBS is used to build complete product lines. It is employed for
  openSUSE and also for SUSE Linux Enterprise products. </para>
 <sect1>
  <title>Requirements for a Product</title>
  <para/>
  <remark>TBD</remark>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Types of Products</title>
  <para> product media, appliance, repository... </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Product Setup in &obsa;</title>
  <para/>
  <remark>TBD</remark>
  <sect2>
   <title>Building Packages</title>
   <para>
    A project is configured in the project metadata.
    <!-- This metadata contains ... These projects contain ...-->
   </para>
   <remark>TBD</remark>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>Setting Up Appliances with &kiwi;</title>
   <para/>
   <remark>TBD</remark>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>Creating Products with &kiwi;</title>
   <para/>
   <remark>TBD</remark>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>Product Line Setup</title>
   <para> Bigger products, like openSUSE or SUSE Linux Enterprise usually
    contain multiple media. These media must be kept in sync in various ways,
    for example for installation patterns, version numbering and other meta
    data. To guarantee this, OBS provides the product definition xml.
    Submitting such a product xml will create all necessary sources for meta
    packages and also all needed &kiwi; source files. </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Release Management</title>
  <para> Products needs usually multiple approval steps and should only be
   released on manual approval. OBS is providing a mechanism which allows to
   copy sources and binaries to another project in this case. To use this the
   release target must be configured inside of a repository definition of the
   project metadata:
  </para>
  <screen>&lt;project name="BuildProject"&gt;
  [...]
  &lt;repository name="BuildRepo"&gt;
    &lt;releasetarget project="ReleaseProject" repository="ReleaseRepo" trigger="manual" /&gt;
    [...]
  &lt;/repository&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;</screen>
   <para>The ReleaseProject must be created before and it should be configured as
   build disabled. The release can be triggered then via
   <command>osc release BuildProject</command> All sources and
   build results will be copied over from BuildProject to the ReleaseProject
   and the publishing will happen afterwards. The operation will happen in
   background since it can take quite some time depending on the project size.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Typical Review Process Setup</title>
  <para/>
  <remark>TBD</remark>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
