<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC
  "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.obs.build_config">
 <title>Build Configuration</title>
 <para>
  The build configuration is needed at least in each base project to define
  the setup of the build system. In addition to that it can be used to
  handle compatibility layers or to switch on or off certain features during
  the build.
 </para>
 <para>
  The build config is reachable via API /source/PROJECT/_config, via
  <command>osc meta prjconf</command> or via webui via Project Config tab.
 </para>
 <section>
  <title>Configuration File Syntax</title>
  <para>
   The build configuration is parsed by OBS in rpm style independent of the
   used packaging format. This means that you can use rpm features like
   macros or conditions in the configuration. All lines consist of the form
   'keyword: arguments'.
  </para>
  <para>
   &lt;PACKAGES&gt; mean binary package provides, but not the full filename.
   For example gcc, but not gcc-1.2.3.i386.rpm. Provides of a package can
   not be used either.
  </para>
  <section>
   <title>Required: &lt;PACKAGES&gt;</title>
   <para>
    Required lines contain one or more packages that always get installed
    for package builds. A change in one of the requires packages triggers a
    new build.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Support: &lt;PACKAGES&gt;</title>
   <para>
    Support lines contain one or more packages which also get installed for
    package builds, but a change in one of the packages does not trigger an
    automatic rebuild. This is useful for packages that most likely do not
    influence the build result, for example 'make', or 'coreutils'.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Preinstall: &lt;PACKAGES&gt;</title>
   <para>
    Preinstall packages are needed to run the package installation program.
    They get unpacked before the VM gets started. Included scripts are NOT
    executed during this phase. However these packages will get installed
    again inside of the VM including script execution.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Keep: &lt;PACKAGES&gt;</title>
   <para>
    To eliminate build cycles the to-be-built package is not installed by
    default, even when it is required. Keep can be used overwrite this
    behaviour. It is usually needed for packages like 'make' that are used
    to build itself. Preinstalled packages are automatically kept, as the
    package installation program needs to work all the time.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>VMInstall: &lt;PACKAGES&gt;</title>
   <para>
    VMInstall is like Preinstall, but these packages get only installed when
    a virtual machine like XEN or KVM is used for building. Usually packages
    like 'mount' are listed here.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Runscripts: &lt;PACKAGES&gt;</title>
   <para>
    Runscripts defines the scripts of preinstalled packages which needs to
    be executed directly after the preinstall phase, before installing the
    remaining packages.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Order: &lt;PACKAGE_A&gt;:&lt;PACKAGE_B&gt;</title>
   <para>
    The build script takes care about the installation order if they are
    defined via dependencies inside of the packages. However, there might be
    dependency loops (reported during setup of the build system) or missing
    dependencies. The Order statement can be used then to give a hint where
    to break the loop. &lt;PACKAGE_A&gt; will get installed before
    &lt;PACKAGE_B&gt;.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>ExportFilter: &lt;REGEXP&gt; &lt;ARCHITECTURES&gt;</title>
   <para>
    The export filter can be used to export build results from one
    architecture to others. This is required when one architecture needs
    packages from another architector for building. The regexp must match
    the resulting binary name of the package. It will export it to all
    listed scheduler architectures. Using a single dot will export it to the
    architecture which was used to build it. So not using a dot there will
    filter the package.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>PublishFilter: &lt;REGEXP&gt; [&lt;REGEXP&gt; [...]]</title>
   <para>
    The publish filter can be used limit the published binary packages in
    public repositories. Packages that match any &lt;REGEXP&gt; will not
    be put into the exported repository. There can be only one line of
    PublishFilter for historic reasons. However, multiple &lt;REGEXP&gt;
    can be given.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Prefer: &lt;PACKAGES&gt;</title>
   <para>
    In case multiple packages satisfy a dependency, the OBS system will
    complain about that situation. This is unlike like most package managing
    tools, which just pick one of the package. Because one of OBS' goal is
    to provide reproducible builds, it reports an error in this case instead
    of chosing a random package. The Prefer: tag lists packages to be
    preferred in case a choice exists. When the package name is prefixed
    with a dash, this is treated as a de-prefer.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Prefer: &lt;PACKAGE_A&gt;:&lt;PACKAGES&gt;</title>
   <para>
    It is possible to define the prefer only when one package is creating
    the choice error. This package must be listed first with a colon.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Ignore: &lt;PACKAGES&gt;</title>
   <para>
    Ignore can be used to break dependencies. This can be usefull to reduce
    the number of needed packages or to break cyclic dependencies. Be
    careful with this feature, as breaking dependencies can have surprising
    results.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Ignore: &lt;PACKAGE_A&gt;:&lt;PACKAGES&gt;</title>
   <para>
    It is possible to define the ignore only for one package. This package
    must be listed first with a colon.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>FileProvides: &lt;FILE&gt; &lt;PACKAGES&gt;</title>
   <para>
    OBS ignores dependendencies to files (instead of package names) by
    default. This is mostly done to reduce the amount of memory needed, as
    the package file lists take up a considerable amount of repository meta
    data. As a workaround, FileProvides can be used to tell the systems
    which packages contain a file. The File needs to have the full path.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Substitute: &lt;PACKAGE_A&gt; &lt;PACKAGES&gt;</title>
   <para>
    It is possible to replace to BuildRequires with other packages. This
    will have only an affect on directly BuildRequired packages, not on
    indirectly required packages.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>BuildFlags: &lt;FLAG&gt;:&lt;VALUE&gt;</title>
   <para>
    This defines flags for the build process. The following values for FLAG
    are usable.
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <simpara><parameter>vmfstype:</parameter> Defines a specific filesystem when building inside of a VM.
        </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara><parameter>kiwiprofile:</parameter> builds the selected profile in kiwi appliance builds.
        </simpara>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>BuildEngine: &lt;ENGINE&gt;</title>
   <para>
    Use an alternative build engine. This is still chained inside of the
    build script for security reasons. Alternatives are mock (for Fedora and
    RedHat) and debootstrap (for Debian). This will avoid differences in the
    build environment setup, but it will also have an effect on speed and
    reduced features. It should only be used when you want to emulate the
    distribution build. debbuild enginge will build deb files out of a spec
    file description. It can be used by the following definition inside of
    the projet build config:
<screen><command>
Repotype: debian
Type: spec
Binarytype: deb
BuildEngine: debbuild
Support: pax
Support: debbuild
Keep: debbuild
           </command></screen>
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>OptFlags: &lt;TARGET_ARCHITECTURE&gt; &lt;FLAGS&gt;</title>
   <para>
    rpm only: Optflags exports compiler flags to the build. They will only
    have an effect when the spec file is using $RPM_OPT_FLAGS. The target
    architecture may be * to affect all architectures.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Type: &lt;TYPE&gt;</title>
   <para>
    Build recepie type. This is the format of the file which provides the
    build description. This gets usually autodetected, but in some rare
    cases it can be set here to either one of these: spec, dsc, kiwi,
    livebuild, arch, preinstallimage
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>BinaryType: &lt;TYPE&gt;</title>
   <para>
    Binary type. This is the format of the files which will be the result of
    the build jobs. This gets usually set depending on the build recepie
    type. In some situations, for example a kiwi build job result gets
    converted into an rpm, it can be used to overwrite it. Possible values
    are: rpm, deb or none
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Target: &lt;TARGET_ARCHITECTURE&gt;</title>
   <para>
    rpm only: Defines the target architecture. This can be used to build for
    i686 on i586 schedulers for example.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>HostArch: &lt;HOST_ARCHITECTURE&gt;</title>
   <para>
    This is used for cross builds. It defines the host architecture used for
    building, while the scheduler architecture remains the target
    architecture.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>type: &lt;TYPE&gt;</title>
   <para>
    Defines the recipe format. Valid values are currently: none, spec, dsc,
    arch, kiwi, preinstallimage. If no type is specified, OBS deduces a type
    from the binary type.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Binarytype: &lt;TYPE&gt;</title>
   <para>
    (OBS 2.4 or later): Sets the binary format used to setup the build
    environment. For example a package with spec build description may use
    and generate deb packages instead of rpms. If no binary type is
    specifed, OBS deduces it from the recipe type. If the recipe type is
    also not set, OBS looks at the Preinstall package list for a hint.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Repotype: &lt;TYPE[:OPTIONS]&gt; ...</title>
   <para>
    Defines the repository format for pulished repositories. Valid values
    are: none, rpm-md, suse, debian, hdlist2, arch, staticlinks. The OPTIONS
    parameter depends on the repository type, for rpm-md the known options
    are 'legacy' to create the old rpm-md format, 'deltainfo' or
    'prestodelta' to create delta rpm packages, 'rsyncable' to use rsyncable
    gzip compression. To split the debug packages in an own published
    repository the option splitdebug:$REPOSIORY_SUFFIX can be used.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Patterntype: &lt;TYPES&gt;</title>
   <para>
    Defines the pattern format. Valid values are: none (default), ymp,
    comps.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Constraint: &lt;SELECTOR&gt; &lt;STRING&gt;</title>
   <para>
    (OBS 2.4 or later): Define build constraints for build jobs. The
    selector is a colon seperated list which gets a string assigned. Please
    see the build job constraints page for details.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Macro Section</title>
  <para>
   The macro section of the build configuration starts behind a Macros: line
   and is only used on rpm builds. The content gets exported to be used by
   rpmbuild during the build. It can be used to export a define using "%key
   value" lines.
  </para>
 </section>
</chapter>
