<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<sect1 version="5.1" xml:id="staging-how-to"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" >
  <title>Staging Workflow</title>
  <para>
    The Build Service is well known for providing an easy way to build and
    distribute binary packages from source code. The packages, grouped together
    in what we call a project, are built every time they are updated. The
    maintainers of the package can choose among a wide range of operating systems
    and hardware architectures to build the packages on. Those continuous
    building processes ensure that the packages are always working for the
    different setups.
  </para>
  <para>
    The maintenance of those packages can be made on a collaborative way via
    Build Service. As shown in the following diagram, the maintainers can create
    a package and then they or any other developer can branch it (make a copy of
    it), can do some changes on its code and can request those changes to be
    applied on the original package. After that, the maintainers usually review
    the request, chat with the developer in case it needs some fixes and end up
    accepting the request. Doing so, the new changes to the code become part of
    the package's source code.
  </para>
  <figure>
   <title>Staging Workflow Basic Schema</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
     <imagedata fileref="staging_workflow_basic_schema.png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
    However, the workflow is not always that easy. Apart from managing
    individual packages, Build Service provides many other functionalities and
    it even allows us to release entire distributions. In a very simplistic way,
    we can say a distribution is just a Build Service project with thousands of
    packages inside. Packages that have been selected to be installed together
    as part of the distribution.
  </para>
  <para>
    When dealing with such a big project, many people request changes in many
    different packages all the time. They have to be reviewed, adjusted and
    tested (built) before being accepted. As you can imagine, it becomes
    nonviable to review the packages one by one. Even if the maintainers check
    that a package is not broken and merge it, it can break everything else for
    conflicts with other packages. To deal with these situations, Build Service
    provides what we call Staging Workflow.
  </para>
  <para>
    The idea behind the Staging Workflow is testing the requests incrementally
    by batches. First, a copy of the original project is created, it is called
    Staging Project and is going to act as a playground. The Staging Managers
    select some of the requests they consider to be belonging together and assign the
    corresponding packages to the Staging Project. This way, the groups of
    packages are going to be tested (built) in one go. Once the Staging Project
    gets built, the changes can be merged to the original project.
  </para>
  <para>
    The Staging Managers can create as many Staging Projects as they require and
    can assign different selections of requests to each of them. It is still tedious
    solving the conflicts that appear between them, but being able to test a lot of
    packages in parallel is much more efficient than doing the same package by
    package.
  </para>
  <para>
    Let's make it clearer with a real example. Imagine we are working on the
    project openSUSE Factory and we start working on its Staging Workflow.
  </para>
  <para>
    Many contributors and maintainers really want some improvements to be
    applied on their packages, so the openSUSE:Factory project receives new
    requests all the time. Among all of them, there are a few that are related
    to Gnome packages, so the Staging Managers decide to stage them together in
    openSUSE:Factory:Staging:A. The Staging Project is an exact copy of the main
    project openSUSE:Factory.
  </para>
  <para>
    The building process begins and, if something gets broken, the Staging
    Managers ask the requester to fix it. This can add even more requests to the
    scene but the goal is always getting a working version of
    openSUSE:Factory:Staging:A by fixing or even discarding some of the
    requests. When the building process finishes successfully, the requested
    changes are merged in the source code of openSUSE:Factory and some other
    batches of requests are staged again and again until we come up with an
    stable version of openSUSE:Factory ready to be released.
  </para>
  <figure>
   <title>Staging Workflow Schema</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
     <imagedata fileref="staging_workflow_schema.png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect2>
    <title>Creating a Staging Workflow</title>
    <para>
      At the moment, it is possible to create a Staging Workflow for any kind of project
      unless the project is already one of the Staging Projects.
    </para>
    <para>
      All the Staging Workflow starts in the tab 'Staging' which can be found on
      the project's page. It will take you to the first step to create a new
      Staging Workflow or to the dashboard if the Staging Workflow already exists.
    </para>
    <para>
      The creation of a Staging Workflow will automatically create two Staging Projects
      as a subproject of the main project. Before creating, we need to select a
      group of managers, they will be in charge of assigning requests to the
      Staging Projects and also excluding requests from the Staging Workflow.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Creating a Staging Workflow for openSUSE:Factory</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="staging_workflow_create.png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <note>
      <para>
        An Admin should previously create the manager groups.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Start Using Staging Workflow</title>
    <para>
      In this view, we can find all the Staging Projects with an associated
      request and their current state.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Staging Workflow Show Screen</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="staging_workflow_show.png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
      <para>
        Table content:
      </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis>Staging Project:</emphasis>
              Shows the Staging Project name, its overall state (see legend),
              and the overall build progress of the packages within the project.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis>Requests:</emphasis>
              Show the associated requests and their current state.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis>Problems:</emphasis>
              Shows build problems of packages within the project and status problems reported to
              the Build Service's Status API by external services like openQA.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Info section:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis>Managers:</emphasis>
              Shows the Staging Managers group.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis>Empty projects:</emphasis>
              Staging projects without assigned requests.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis>Backlog:</emphasis>
              List of requests that can be assigned to a Staging Project.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis>Ready:</emphasis>
              List of requests that were in the backlog and have an accepted review.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis>Excluded:</emphasis>
              List of requests excluded from this Staging Workflow.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Delete a Staging Workflow</title>
    <para>
      Next to the title, there is a icon that allows us to delete the Staging Workflow.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Staging Workflow Delete Icon</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="staging_workflow_delete_icon.png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      By clicking on the delete icon on the Staging Workflow index page, we are able
      to delete a Staging Workflow.
    </para>
    <para>
      By selecting the associated Staging Projects in the appearing modal
      window, we are able to delete them as well. If not selected, they will
      remain as regular subprojects.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Delete a Staging Workflow</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="staging_workflow_delete.png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Configure a Staging Workflow</title>
    <para>
      Next to the title, there is a link to the Staging Workflow configuration's page.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Staging Workflow Configure Icon</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="staging_workflow_configure_icon.png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      From the configuration page it is possible to delete a Staging Project,
      create one from scratch or create a copy of an existent one. But also to
      change the Managers Group of the Staging Workflow.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Configuring a Staging Workflow</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="staging_workflow_configuration.png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <note>
      <para>
        Changing the Managers Group of a Staging Workflow will automatically unassign
        the old group and assign the new group to the related Staging Projects.
      </para>
    </note>
    <sect3>
      <title>Create Staging Project from Scratch</title>
      <para>
        Right after the creation of a Staging Workflow, two new Staging Projects are
        automatically created and assigned to it: Staging:A and Staging:B. However,
        it is also possible to create a new Staging Project from scratch.
      </para>
      <para>
        On the Staging Workflow dashboard, click on configure icon next to the title and
        then on <emphasis>Create Staging Project</emphasis> to add a name for the new
        Staging Project.
      </para>
      <figure>
       <title>Create a New Staging Project</title>
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="staging_project_create.png"/>
        </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Create Staging Project from a Template</title>
      <para>
        It is possible to create a Staging Project from a template. Inside Staging Workflow's
        configuration page, simply choose the Staging Project you want to copy
        from (the template), click on its Copy icon and add a new name. The
        Staging Project copy is processed in the background, so there might be a
        delay before it shows up.
      </para>
      <figure>
       <title>Copy Staging Project from Template</title>
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="staging_project_copy.png"/>
        </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Staging Project</title>
    <para>
      A Staging Project contains requests assigned by a Staging Manager. There is
      an overview page for a Staging Project, where you can find more
      detailed information about the requests, reviews and checks.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>Looking into a Staging Project</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="staging_project_show.png"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Obsolete Requests:</emphasis>
          Requests that were declined, revoked or superseded.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Missing Reviews:</emphasis>
          Requests with pending reviews.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Building Repositories:</emphasis>
          List of packages that are still building.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Broken Packages:</emphasis>
          List of packages with failing builds.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Checks:</emphasis>
          List of checks of the Staging Project.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      All the actions performed on requests that are assigned to the Staging
      Project are tracked. They are listed in the 'History' section.
    </para>
    <figure>
     <title>History</title>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="staging_project_history.png"/>
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
    <title>Working with Requests in Staging Workflow</title>
    <sect3>
      <title>Exclude Requests</title>
      <para>
        Sometimes it can be useful to exclude a request and don't let it be
        available in the Backlog. This can prevent the staging project from
        being assigned with requests we are sure are causing conflicts, have
        some missing dependencies or have to wait for other request to be
        accepted.
      </para>
      <para>
        By clicking on the 'Excluded' link on the 'Infos' section, it is possible
        to exclude requests or bring back already excluded ones.
      </para>
      <figure>
       <title>Exclude Requests</title>
        <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="staging_workflow_exclude_requests.png"/>
         </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
