<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.1" xml:id="cha.obs.build_process"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" >
 <title>Build Process</title>
 <para>
  Each package build is created in a fresh environment. This is done to
  ensure that all dependencies are available and that every later build
  produces identical results.
 </para>
 <sect1>
  <title>Definition of a Build Process</title>
  <para/>
  <remark>TBD</remark>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>How does a build process work</title>
  <para>
   All sources and binaries which are hosted inside &obs; are organized in
   projects. Projects host sources inside of &obsa; packages. The sources are
   build according to the repository configuration inside of the project.
  </para>
  <sect2>
   <title>Preinstall Phase</title>
   <para>
    This phase depends on the type of the buildroot (building
    environment). &obsa; supports three different types of buildroots:
   </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       chroot
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       XEN
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       KVM
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist> 
    <para>
    In the preinstall phase, the OBS Worker creates a small
    base system (chroot or VM Image) with manually extracted packages (file
    system, coreutils, binutils, rpm/debutils, etc.), copies all necessary
    build requirements into the base system. </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>Install Phase</title>
   <para>
    Depending of the chosen build root, the worker starts a Xen or KVM
    virtual machine or enters the build root. If this was successful, the
    install phase reinstalls all base packages from above and additionally all
    packages you have defined in your build recipe. After this phase the
    environment is ready to process the build recipe.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>Package Build</title>
   <remark>
    FIXME: Terminology: Definition of buildroot? Is buildroot a command? I
    would have presumed this to be a location not a command or other type of
    active thingie. - sknorr, 2017-08-24
   </remark>
   <para>
    Depending on the type of package, the buildroot executes different build
    commands:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      RPM-based distributions: <command>rpmbuild</command>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Debian-based distributions: <command>dpkg-buildpackage</command>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Arch Linux: <command>pacman</command>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    How the build continues depends on the quality and the type of your build
    recipe. In most cases, the source code will be compiled now and then be
    packed into the chosen package format.
   </para>
   <para>
    To improve package quality, on RPM-based distributions there are
    additional security checks and a linter called <command>rpmlint</command>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>After the Build</title>
   <para>
    The generated packages are taken from the worker, are signed by the
    &obsa; signer and are published to the Repository.
   </para>
   <remark>
    FIXME: Terminology -- "signing server" instead of "signer"?
    - sknorr, 2017-08-24
   </remark>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Different Ways of Building</title>
  <para/>
  <remark>TBD</remark>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Security Aspects</title>
  <para/>
  <remark>TBD</remark>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
