<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC
  "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<section id="cha.obs.admin.appliance">
 <title>OBS Appliances</title>
 <para>
  This chapter gives an overview over the different OBS appliances and how to
  deploy them for production use.
 </para>
 <section>
  <title>Server Appliance</title>
  <para>
   The OBS server appliance contains a recent openSUSE distribution with a
   pre-installed and pre-configured OBS frontend, backend and worker. The
   operating system on this appliance adapts to the hardware on first boot and
   defaults to automatic IP and DNS configuration via DHCP.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Worker Appliance</title>
  <para>
   The OBS worker appliance includes a recent openSUSE distribtion and the OBS
   worker component. The operating system on this appliance adapts to the
   hardware on first boot, defaults to automatic IP and DNS configuration via
   DHCP and OBS server discovery via SLP.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Image Types</title>
  <para>
   There are different types of OBS appliance images.
   <table id='cha.obs.best-practices.appliance_types'>
    <title>Appliance Types</title>
    <tgroup cols='2' align='left'>
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry>Filename Suffix</entry>
       <entry>Appliance for</entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
                .vdi
              </entry>
       <entry><ulink url="https://www.virtualbox.org/">VirtualBox</ulink>.
              </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
                .vmdk
              </entry>
       <entry><ulink url="http://www.vmware.com/">VMware</ulink>
                Workstation and Player.
                <note>
         <para>
          Our VirtualBox images are usually better tested.
         </para>
        </note>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
                .qcow2
              </entry>
       <entry><ulink url="http://qemu.org">QEMU/KVM</ulink>.
              </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
                .raw
              </entry>
       <entry>
                 Direct writing to a block device
              </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
                .tgz
              </entry>
       <entry>
                 Deploying via PXE from a central server
              </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </table>
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Deployment</title>
  <para>
   To help you deploy the OBS server appliance to a hard disk there is an basic
   installer that you can boot from an USB stick. The installer can be found on
   the <ulink url="http://openbuildservice.org/download/">OBS Download
   page</ulink>.
  </para>
  <para>
   The image can be written to an USB stick to boot from it:
<screen><command>
xzcat obs-server-install.x86_64.raw.xz > /dev/sdX
      </command></screen>
  </para>
  <warning>
   <para>
    /dev/sdX is the main device of your USB stick. Do NOT put it into a
    partition like /dev/sda1. If you use the wrong device, you will destroy all
    data on it!
   </para>
  </warning>
  <para>
   How to deploy the other image types deeply depends on your virtualization
   setup. Describing this is out of scope for this guide, sorry.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Separating Data from the System</title>
  <para>
   For production use you want to seperate the OBS data from operating system
   of the appliance so you can re-deploy the appliance without touching your
   OBS data. This can be achieved by createing a LVM volume group with the name
   "OBS". This volume group should be as large as possible because it is
   getting used by the OBS backend for data storage and the OBS workers for
   root/swap/cache file systems. To create a LVM volume prepare a partition of
   type "8e" and create the LVM via
<screen><command>
pvcreate /dev/sdX1
vgcreate "OBS" /dev/sdX1
    </command></screen>
  </para>
  <para>
   Additionally if the OBS volume group contains a logical volume named
   "server", it will be used as the data partition for the server.
<screen><command>
lvcreate "OBS" -n "server"
mkfs.xfs /dev/OBS/server
    </command></screen>
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Updating the Appliance</title>
  <para>
   All images come pre-configured with the right set of repositories and can be
   updated via the system tools YaST or <command>zypper</command> at any time.
   Another way to update is to re-deploy the entire image.
  </para>
  <warning>
   <para>
    If you re-deploy the entire image, keep in mind that you need to have your
    data directory (/srv/obs) on a separate storage (LVM volume, partition
    etc.) otherwise it will get deleted!
   </para>
  </warning>
 </section>
</section>
