<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.1" xml:id="cha-obs-binary-tracking"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Binary Package Tracking</title>
 <para>
  Products and updates to them are often officially supported by a company.
  To allow giving such support, there is binary package tracking. This
  feature allows checking which exact version of a package was shipped at
  what time. This feature is often important for release managers,
  maintenance engineers, QA engineers and supporters.
 </para>
 <para>
  &obsa; can track these binary packages and offer a database to search
  them.
 </para>
 <sect1>
  <title>Which Binaries Are Tracked?</title>
  <para>
   All binaries which are released into projects providing
   <literal>kind=maintenance_release</literal> are tracked. In addition to
   that, the &obsa; administrator can configure additional projects via the
   <literal>packtrack</literal> setting in <filename>BSConfig.pm</filename>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>What Data Is Tracked?</title>
  <para> In short the information to identify a binary, its building place and
   timestamps are tracked. In addition to that also information about possible
   successor versions or if the binary got removed in the meantime. If products
   do reference the repositories the search interface offers also a listing of
   products which are supposed to use it. Either as part of the product media
   itself or in one of its update repositories. </para>
  <sect2>
   <title>Binary Identifier</title>
   <para>
    A binary is identified by the following information which is extracted from
    components of the file path of the binary:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Repository:</title>
      <para>
       Where is the binary hosted?
      </para>
     </formalpara>
     <para>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Name:</title>
      <para>
       Name of the binary file
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Epoch:</title>
      <para>
       The epoch version (optional, usually not used)
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Version:</title>
      <para>
       The version
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Release:</title>
      <para>
       The release number
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Architecture:</title>
      <para>
       The hardware architecture
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Medium:</title>
      <para>
       Name of the medium (exists only for product builds)
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>Binary Information</title>
   <para> Additional information about a binary is information which gets
    updated when a binary gets added or replaced. </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para> operation, got the binary added, removed or modified </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> publish time, aka the time when the repository gets published by
      OBS. This is not the same time as when the release action got invoked.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> build time </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> obsolete time, exists only when a binary gets removed or replaced
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> supportstatus, meta information about the level of support which is
      granted for the binary at the time of releasing it. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> updateinfo id from rpm-md repository </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> maintainer of the binary who has prepared this update </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> disturl, the exact identifier to the source and build repository
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>Product information</title>
   <para> Additional information about products referencing to this binary. </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para> updatefor: the listed products do reference the repository as
      update channel. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> product: exists when the binary was part of a product medium
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 condition="tbd">
  <title>&osccmd; Search Interface</title>
  <para/>
  <remark>TBD: not yet implemented (?) </remark>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 condition="tbd">
  <title>Web UI Search Interface</title>
  <para/>
  <remark>TBD: not yet implemented (?) </remark>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>API Search Interface</title>
  <para>
   The search of released binaries is provided via the following API endpoints:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     /search/released/binary/id : short form, just listing the matched
     binary identifiers. See the <link
     xlink:href="https://api.opensuse.org/apidocs/#/Search/get_search_released_binary_id">reference documentation</link>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>/search/released/binary : long form, provides all other tracked
     information as described above. See the <link
     xlink:href="https://api.opensuse.org/apidocs/#/Search/get_search_released_binary">reference documentation</link>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   Please visit the before mentioned links to get details and several examples of how to
   use these API endpoints.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
