<!DOCTYPE preface
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<!-- HINT: Currently no ID as it is used by different books -->
<preface version="5.1"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>About this Guide</title>
 <info/>
 <para> This guide is part of the &obs; documentation.
  These books are considered to contain only reviewed content, establishing the
  reference documentation of &obsa;.
 </para>
 <para>
  This guide does not focus on a specific &obsa; version.
  <remark>
   That is hogwash: It just documents whatever was available at the time of
   writing. - sknorr, 2017-08-23
  </remark>
  It is also not a replacement of the documentation inside of the <link
   xlink:href="https://en.opensuse.org/Portal:Build_Service"
  >&opensuse; Wiki</link>. However, content from the wiki may be included in
  these books in a consolidated form.
 </para>

 <xi:include href="common_intro_available_doc_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="common_intro_feedback_i.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="common_intro_typografie_i.xml"/>

 <sect1>
  <title>Lend a Hand?</title>
  <para>
   The &obsa; documentation is written by the community. In other words: You
   can help!
  </para>
  <para>
   Especially as an advanced user or an adminstrator of
   &obsa;, there will be many topics where you can pitch in even if your
   English is not the most polished. Conversely, if you are not very
   experienced with &obsa; but your English is good: We rely on community
   editors to improve the language.
  </para>
  <para>
   This guide is written in DocBook XML which can be converted to HTML or PDF
   documentation.
  </para>
  <para>
   To clone the source of this guide, use Git:
  </para>
  <screen><command>git clone</command> https://github.com/openSUSE/obs-docu.git</screen>
  <para>
   To learn how to validate and generate the &obsa; documentation, see the
   file <filename>README</filename>.
  </para>
  <para>
   To submit changes, use GitHub pull requests:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Fork your own copy of the repository.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Commit your changes into the forked repository.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Create a pull request. This can be done at
     <link xlink:href="https://github.com/openSUSE/obs-docu"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
   It is even possible to host instance-specific content in the official
   Git repository, but it needs to be tagged correctly. For example,
   parts of this documentation are tagged as <tag>&lt;para
   os="opensuse"&gt;</tag>. In this case, the paragraph
   will become only visible when creating the &opensuse; version of a guide.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</preface>
