<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<sect1 version="5.1" xml:id="cha-obs-admin-appliance"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>OBS Appliances</title>
 <para> This chapter gives an overview over the different OBS appliances and
  how to deploy them for production use. </para>
 <sect2>
  <title>Server Appliance</title>
  <para> The &obsa; server appliance contains a recent &opensuse; distribution with
   a pre-installed and pre-configured OBS front-end, back-end and worker. The
   operating system on this appliance adapts to the hardware on first boot and
   defaults to automatic IP and DNS configuration via DHCP. </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>Worker Appliance</title>
  <para> The &obsa; worker appliance includes a recent &opensuse; distribution and
   the &obsa; worker component. The operating system on this appliance adapts to
   the hardware on first boot, defaults to automatic IP and DNS configuration
   via DHCP and &obsa; server discovery via SLP. </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>Image Types</title>
  <para> There are different types of &obsa; appliance images.</para>
   <table
    xml:id="cha.obs.best-practices.appliance_types">
    <title>Appliance Types</title>
    <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry>File Name Suffix</entry>
       <entry>Appliance for</entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry> .vdi </entry>
       <entry><link xlink:href="https://www.virtualbox.org/">VirtualBox</link>.
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry> .vmdk </entry>
       <entry>
        <para><link xlink:href="http://www.vmware.com/">VMware</link>
         Workstation and Player.</para>
        <note>
         <para> Our VirtualBox images are usually better tested. </para>
        </note>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry> .qcow2 </entry>
       <entry><link xlink:href="http://qemu.org">QEMU/KVM</link>. </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry> .raw </entry>
       <entry> Direct writing to a block device </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry> .tgz </entry>
       <entry> Deploying via PXE from a central server </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </table>
  
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>Deployment</title>
  <para> To help you deploy the OBS server appliance to a hard disk there is a
   basic installer that you can boot from a USB stick. The installer can be
   found on the <link xlink:href="http://openbuildservice.org/download/">OBS
    Download page</link>. </para>
  <para> The image can be written to a USB stick to boot from it:</para>
  <screen><command>xzcat obs-server-install.x86_64.raw.xz &gt; /dev/sdX</command></screen>
  <warning>
   <para> /dev/sdX is the main device of your USB stick. Do NOT put it into a
    partition like /dev/sda1. If you use the wrong device, you will destroy all
    data on it! </para>
  </warning>
  <para> How to deploy the other image types deeply depends on your
   virtualization setup. Describing this is out of scope for this guide, sorry.
  </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>Separating Data from the System</title>
  <para> For production use you want to separate the OBS data from operating
   system of the appliance so you can re-deploy the appliance without touching
   your OBS data. This can be achieved by creating an LVM volume group with the
   name "OBS". This volume group should be as large as possible because it is
   getting used by the OBS back-end for data storage and the OBS workers for
   root/swap/cache file systems. To create an LVM volume prepare a partition of
   type "8e" and create the LVM via</para>
   <screen>
<command>pvcreate /dev/sdX1</command>
<command>vgcreate "OBS" /dev/sdX1</command>
</screen>
  <para>
   Additionally, if the OBS volume group contains a logical volume named
   <quote>server</quote>, it will be used as the data partition for the server.
  </para>
  <screen>
<command>lvcreate "OBS" -n "server"</command>
<command>mkfs.xfs /dev/OBS/server</command></screen>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>Updating the Appliance</title>
  <para> All images come pre-configured with the right set of repositories and
   can be updated via the system tools YaST or <command>zypper</command> at any
   time. Another way to update is to re-deploy the entire image. </para>
  <warning>
   <para> If you re-deploy the entire image, keep in mind that you need to have
    your data directory (<filename>/srv/obs</filename>) on a separate storage
    (LVM volume, partition etc.) otherwise it will be deleted! </para>
  </warning>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
