<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC
  "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<section id="cha.obs.admin.components">
 <title>OBS Components</title>
 <para>
   The OBS is not a monolithic server, it consists of multiple daemons that
   fulfill different tasks.
 </para>
 <figure>
  <title>Simplified OBS Component Overview</title>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="obs_components.png" width="800" />
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </figure>
 <section>
   <title>Frontend</title>
   <para>
     The OBS Frontend is a Ruby on Rails application that manages the access and
     manipulation of the OBS data. It provides a web user interface and an
     application programming interface to do so. Both can be used to create,
     read, update and delete users, projects/packages, requests and other
     objects. It also implements additional sub-systems like authentication,
     search or email notifications.
   </para>
 </section>
 <section>
   <title>Backend</title>
   <para>
     The OBS Backend is a collection of Perl applications that manage the source
     files and build jobs of the OBS.
   </para>
   <section>
     <title>Source Server</title>
     <para>
       Maintains the source repository and project/package configurations.
       It provides a http interface, which is the only interface for the Frontend
       and it may forward requests to further backend services. Each OBS installation has one
       Source Server only. It maintains the "sources", "trees" and "projects" directories.
     </para>
   </section>
   <section>
     <title>Repository Server</title>
     <para>
       A repository server provides access to the binaries via a http interface. 
       It is used by the frontend via the source server only.
       Workers are using the server for registration, requesting the needed binaries
       for the build jobs and are storing the result.
       Notifications for schedulers are also created by repository servers.
       Each OBS installation has at least one repository servers. A larger
       installation using partitioning has one on each partition.
     </para>
   </section>
   <section>
     <title>Scheduler</title>
     <para>
       A scheduler is calculating the need for build jobs. It detects 
       changes in sources, project configurations or in binaries used in
       the build environment. It is responsible for starting jobs in the right order
       and integrating the built binary packages.
       Each OBS installation has one scheduler per available architecture and partition.
       It maintains the content of the "build" directory.
     </para>
   </section>
   <section>
     <title>Dispatcher</title>
     <para>
       The dispatcher takes a job (created by the scheduler) and is assigning it 
       to a free worker. It also checks possible build constraints to verify that
       the worker qualifies for the job. It only notifies a worker about a job,
       the worker is downloading the needed resources itself afterwards.
       Each OBS installation has one dispatcher per partition (only one of them
       is the master dispatcher).
     </para>
   </section>
   <section>
     <title>Publisher</title>
     <para>
       The publisher is processing publish events from the scheduler for finished
       repositories. It is merging the build result of all architectures into 
       a defined directory structure, creates the needed meta data and may sync it 
       to a download server.
       It maintains the content of the "repos" directory on the backend.
       Each OBS installation has one publisher per partition.
     </para>
   </section>
   <section>
     <title>Worker</title>
     <para>
       The workers register at the repository servers. They receive build jobs
       from the dispatcher. Afterwards they download sources from source server
       and the needed binaries from the repository server(s). They are building
       the package using the build script and sending the result back to the
       repository server.
       A worker can run on the same host as the other services, but most OBS
       installations have dedicated hardware for the workers.
     </para>
   </section>
   <section>
     <title>Signer</title>
     <para>
       The signer is handling signing events and is calling an external tool to
       execute the signing. Each OBS installation usally has one signer per partition and
       also on the source server installation.
     </para>
   </section>
   <section>
     <title>Warden</title>
     <para>
       The warden is monitoring the workers and detects crashed or hanging workers.
       Their build jobs will be canceld restarted on another host then.
       Each OBS installation can have one dodup service running on each partition.
     </para>
   </section>
   <section>
     <title>Download on Demand Updater (dodup)</title>
     <para>
       The download on demand updater is monitoring all external repositories which
       are defined as download on demand resources. It is polling for changes
       in the meta data and redownloads the meta data in case. The scheduler will
       be notified to recalculate the build jobs depending on these repositories 
       afterwards.
       Each OBS installation can have one dodup service running on each partition.
     </para>
   </section>
   <section>
     <title>Delta Store</title>
     <para>
        To be written...
       The delta store daemon is maintaining the deltas in the source storage.
       Multiple obscpio archives can be stored in one deltastore to avoid
       duplication on disk. This services is calculating the delta and maintains 
       the delta store.
       Each OBS installation can have one delta store process running next to
       the source serv.er
     </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Command Line Client</title>
    <para>
      The Open Build Service Commander (osc) is a Python application with a
      Subversion style command-line interface. It can be used to to manipulate or
      query data from the OBS through its application programming interface.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Content Delivery Server</title>
    <para>
      The OBS is agnostic about how you serve build results to your users. It will
      just write repositories to disk. But many people sync these repositories to
      some content delivery system like
      <ulink url="http://mirrorbrain.org/">MirrorBrain</ulink>.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Requirements</title>
   <para>
     We highly recommend, and in fact only test, installations on the
     <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/products/server/">SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</ulink>
     and <ulink url="http://www.opensuse.org">openSUSE</ulink> operating systems. However,
     we are aware that there a few installations on debian and fedora systems out there.
   </para>
   <para>
     The OBS also needs a SQL database (MySQL or MariaDB) for persistent and a
     memcache daemon for volatile data.
   </para>
  </section>
</section>
