<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<sect1 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1"
 xml:id="obs-spider-identification">
 <title>Spider Identification</title>
 <para> OBS is hiding specific parts/pages of the application from search
  crawlers (DuckDuckGo, Google, etc.), mostly for performance reasons. Which
  user-agent strings are identified as crawlers configured in the file
   <filename>/srv/www/obs/api/config/crawler-user-agents.json</filename>. </para>
 <para> To update that list, you must run the command <command>bundle exec rake
   voight_kampf:import_user_agents</command> in the root directory of your OBS
  instance. This downloads the current crawler list of user agents as a JSON
  file into the <filename>config/</filename> directory of the Rails
  application. </para>
 <para> If you want to extend or edit this list, switch to the
   <filename>config/</filename> directory and open the
   <filename>crawler-user-agents.json</filename> file with the editor of your
  choice. The content can look like this:
  </para>
  <screen>[
   {
       "pattern": "Googlebot\\/",
       "url": "http://www.google.com/bot.html"
   },
   {
       "pattern": "Googlebot-Mobile"
   },
   {
       "pattern": "Googlebot-Image"
   },
   [...]
]</screen>
 
 <para> To add a new bot to this list, a pattern must be defined. This is
  required to identify a bot. Almost all bots have their own user agent that
  they are sending to a Web server to identify them. For example, the user
  agent of the Googlebot looks like this:</para>
  <screen>Mozilla/5.0 (compatible; Googlebot/2.1; +http://www.google.com/bot.html)</screen>
  <para>To choose the pattern for the new bot, compare the user agent of the bot you
  want to identify with others and look for a part that is unique (like in the
  Googlebot example, the part: Googlebot). </para>
 <para> Let's assume we want to add the bot Geekobot to the list of bots and
  the user agent looks like this:</para>
  <screen>Mozilla/5.0 (compatible; Geekobot/2.1; +https://www.opensuse.org)</screen>
  <para>Our unique part would be Geekobot. So we add a new entry to the list of bots:</para>
  <screen>[
   {
       "pattern": "Googlebot\\/",
       "url": "http://www.google.com/bot.html"
   },
   {
       "pattern": "Googlebot-Mobile"
   },
   {
       "pattern": "Googlebot-Image"
   },
   [...]
   {
       "pattern": "Geekobot"
   }
]</screen>
 <note>
  <para>You can also use regular expressions in the pattern element.</para>
 </note>
 <para> Save the file and restart the Rails application and the bot Geekobot
  should be identified properly. </para>
</sect1>
