<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1"
 xml:id="obs-cha-troubleshooting">
 <title>Troubleshooting</title>
 <info/>

 <para>Here are two major classes of problems regarding the &obs;:
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para> Normal package build errors </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para> Bugs, resource shortage or config issues caused issues </para>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
 <para>The first category are errors like missing dependent packages in the
  build environment, errors during compiling or linking, errors in the build
  description and so on. Most of them should not happen if the packager does
  test the build locally before committing it to the OBS. This type of problems
  is not covered by this chapter.</para>
 <sect1 xml:id="general-hints">
  <title>General Hints</title>
  <para>If you detect unexpected behavior of the open build service, you
   should follow some rules to locate the problem:</para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para> Consult the log files, for the back-end look at
      <emphasis>/srv/obs/log</emphasis> for the back-end log files and
      <emphasis>/srv/www/obs/api/log</emphasis> for the front-end log files.
     See the Log files <xref linkend="log-files"/> for more details.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para> Consult the normal OS system logs and the kernel log (dmesg) if
     here are reported system or HW problems. </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para> Check if all services are running on the back-end and front-end.
     See the OBS Architecture in reference book for details. </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para> Try to find an easy way to reproduce the problem. </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para> To check whether this issue was already reported, see <link
      xlink:href="https://github.com/openSUSE/open-build-service"/>. </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para> Use search machines (Google) to find out if others did also run
     into this problem. If you are lucky, you will find a fix or workaround as
     well. </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para> If you create a new bug report, include all information to
     reproduce the problem and the complete error message/error log if here are
     any. </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="debug-frontend-problems">
  <title>Debugging Front-end Problems</title>
  <para>If you get unexpected results from submitting commands with the
    <emphasis role="strong"><emphasis>osc</emphasis></emphasis> tool, you can
   use the debug feature of the tools to find more information about what
   happened.</para>
  <para>osc debug options</para>
  <screen>--debugger         jump into the debugger before executing anything
--post-mortem      jump into the debugger in case of errors
-t, --traceback    print call trace in case of errors
-H, --http-debug   debug HTTP traffic (filters some headers)
--http-full-debug  debug HTTP traffic (filters no headers)
-d, --debug        print info useful for debugging</screen>
  <para>The <emphasis role="strong"
    ><emphasis>--debugger</emphasis></emphasis> and <emphasis role="strong"
     ><emphasis>--post-mortem</emphasis></emphasis> are only suitable for
    <emphasis>osc</emphasis> developers. If you get an error message from osc,
   the <emphasis role="strong"><emphasis>-t, --traceback</emphasis></emphasis>
   can give the developer some more information about the problem. The
    <emphasis role="strong"><emphasis>-H, --http-debug</emphasis></emphasis>
   and <emphasis role="strong"
    ><emphasis>--http-full-debug</emphasis></emphasis> options are useful to
   see the raw answers of OBS API, often this gives a hint what maybe wrong. If
   you report a problem regarding the <emphasis role="strong"
     ><emphasis>osc</emphasis></emphasis> tool, it may help to include the osc
   output with <emphasis role="strong">additional *<emphasis>--http-debug
     --traceback</emphasis></emphasis> options.</para>
  <warning>
   <para>With <emphasis role="strong"
     ><emphasis>--http-full-debug</emphasis></emphasis> all http headers are
    included, this may include user data and authentication stuff so review and
    replace such data with XXXXXXXX or so before you post it on the
    internet.</para>
  </warning>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
