<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC
  "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.obs.best-practices.localsetup" os="opensuse;novell">
 <title id="cha.obs.best-practices.localsetup.title">OBS Local Setup</title>
 <para>
  This chapter explains how you could setup/Install/test OBS in your system.
  This chapter is written for those who are not so familiar with Linux and OBS.
  So in case you are confident to setup OBS, skip this chapter.
  Following would be explained in this chapter.
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     OBS 1 click install, then manual setup in openSUSE 13.1;
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     OBS 1 click install, then manual setup in SLES11;
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     OBS test run on Microsoft Windows using VMware player;
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     OBS appliance installed manually in a VirtualBox.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  Unfortunately, didn't have a chance to install OBS in other Linux
  distribution yet. The last section will explain your first steps with the new
  OBS server.
 </para>
 <para>
  How you could install and purchase openSUSE 13.1 and SLES12 will not be
  explained in this chapter. VMware player install and purchase also will not be
  explained. For these topics, you could visit for help:
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://software.opensuse.org/131/en">http://software.opensuse.org/131/en</ulink>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/products/server/">http://www.suse.com/products/server/</ulink>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://my.vmware.com/web/vmware/free#desktop_end_user_computing/vmware_player/6_0">http://my.vmware.com/web/vmware/free#desktop_end_user_computing/vmware_player/6_0</ulink>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </para>
 <section>
  <title>OBS test run on Microsoft Windows using VMware player</title>
  <para>
   Those who are not familiar with Linux can run and test OBS. To run and test
   OBS in Windows, you could use a virtual machine program such as VMware or
   VirtualBox, etc. This chapter explains, how you can run OBS using VMware
   player. To check and test with VirtualBox or another virtual machine,
   check in below.
  </para>
  <para>
   After you are done installing VMware player on Windows, you need to download
   the OBS appliance program. You could get OBS appliance file by visiting
   <ulink url="http://openbuildservice.org/download/other/">http://openbuildservice.org/download/other/</ulink>
   and clicking on <guibutton>VirtualBox/VMware Image</guibutton>. After
   downloading, uncompress with some Windows archiving program that understands
   the <filename>.tar.bz2</filename> file format.
  </para>
  <para>
   Now, open <application>VMware Player</application> application and select
   <menuchoice> <guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Open a Virtual
   Machine</guimenuitem> </menuchoice>, or you could press
   <keycombo action="simul"> <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> <keycap>O</keycap>
   </keycombo> directly. Open the decompressed virtual machine in
   <guilabel>Open Virtual Machine</guilabel> dialog box. Click on
   <guibutton>Play virtual machine</guibutton> icon or hyper link in VMware
   player.
  </para>
  <para>
   At the Linux prompt, you can login using "root" as a login name and
   "opensuse" as a password. Now, OBS local instance should be already loaded
   and running in your system. To make sure that the OBS Web UI is successfully up and
   running, open the OBS Web UI.
  </para>
  <para>
   To access OBS Web user interface, open your web browser and try the address
   <literal>http://vm.ip.address</literal>. You can check the virtual machine's IP address by using
   <command>ifconfig</command> Linux command. Now, you probably could see a
   screen like the one below in your window:
  </para>
<!-- fs 2011-10-13: Image missing

    <figure>
      <title>OBS_Run_On_Windows</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="obs_run_on_windows.png" width="800" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    -->
  <para>
   To login your local OBS instance, you could use default login name as
   "Admin" and password as "opensuse". Check if you could login properly by
   clicking <guibutton>Login</guibutton> on your local OBS instance Web UI.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>OBS 1 click install on openSUSE 13.1</title>
  <para>
   This section explains, how you can install OBS on top of openSUSE 13.1. Open
   your web browser and go to that URL
   <ulink url="http://download.opensuse.org/repositories/openSUSE:/Tools/openSUSE_13.1/OBS_Server.ymp">http://download.opensuse.org/repositories/openSUSE:/Tools/openSUSE_13.1/OBS_Server.ymp</ulink>
  </para>
  <para>
   This YaST Meta Package file lets you install OBS by 1 click. In case you are
   using openSUSE 11.2 or below version, check if you could find 1 click
   install file in this URL
   <ulink url="http://en.opensuse.org/openSUSE:Build_Service_Installation_SUSE">http://en.opensuse.org/openSUSE:Build_Service_Installation_SUSE</ulink>
  </para>
  <para>
   After you click on the above URL, you would see <guilabel>Opening
   OBS_Server.ymp</guilabel> window, Select default selection which is
   <guilabel>Open with YaST Meta Package Handler</guilabel> and press
   <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button. Then <guilabel>OBS_Server Installation -
   YaST</guilabel> window will appear. Select <guibutton>Next</guibutton>
   button after that till you get successful OBS setup message.
  </para>
  <para>
   TIPS : In case you didn't install libMagickCore.so.2 in openSUSE, you might
   face dependency warning. In that case, stop the OBS install by pressing
   <guibutton>Abort</guibutton> button in <guilabel>OBS_Server Installation -
   YaST</guilabel> window. Then search and install libMagickCore using a search
   engine like Google or others and repeat above processes. Then you will get
   an OBS setup message.
  </para>
  <para>
   Now, OBS Server is installed in your openSUSE. To run OBS server, you need
   to work on several further steps. Open
   /usr/share/doc/packages/obs-api/README.SETUP file. To run OBS server, you
   need to follow each step of README.SETUP carefully based on your system
   situation. You can also find this <filename>README.SETUP</filename> file in
   our public
   <ulink url="https://github.com/openSUSE/open-build-service/blob/master/dist/README.SETUP.md">git
   repository</ulink>. If you are using our stable release, you might want to
   switch to the corresponding branch, eg.
   <ulink url="https://github.com/openSUSE/open-build-service/blob/2.7/dist/README.SETUP">2.7</ulink>.
  </para>
  <para>
   If you follow instructions from README.SETUP file, you should be able to run
   OBS server in your system. There are several tips that I would like to
   comment regarding README.SETUP file.
  </para>
  <para>
   TIP #1 : Check <guilabel>3.1 Initialize fresh Database</guilabel>. It might
   be described as
  </para>
<screen>
# cd /srv/www/obs/api/
# sudo RAILS_ENV="production" rake db:setup
# sudo chown lighttpd.lighttpd log/*

# cd /srv/www/obs/webui/
# sudo RAILS_ENV="production" rake db:setup
# sudo chown lighttpd.lighttpd log/*
</screen>
  <para>
   but it should be
  </para>
<screen>
# cd /srv/www/obs/api/
# sudo RAILS_ENV="production" rake db:migrate
# sudo chown lighttpd.lighttpd log/*

# cd /srv/www/obs/webui/
# sudo RAILS_ENV="production" rake db:migrate
# sudo chown lighttpd.lighttpd log/*
</screen>
  <para>
   For more information, see
   <ulink url="https://en.opensuse.org/openSUSE:Build_Service_Installation_SUSE"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   TIP #2 : If you get fail message because of "apisrv" in "6. Using osc with
   your local build service:", try apiurl instead.
  </para>
  <para>
   You might face some issues during process to follow README.SETUP file. If
   you read and follow instructions carefully, you could run OBS local instance
   on your system successfully.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>OBS 1 click install on SLES (SUSE Linux Enterprise Server) 12</title>
  <para>
   1 click install for OBS in SLES12. This section explains how you install OBS
   in SLES12. Installation of OBS in SLES12 is quite similar to OBS install
   method on openSUSE. I would skip same contents so you might need to have a
   look for prior section "OBS 1 click install on openSUSE 13.1".
  </para>
  <para>
   Before you install OBS on SLES12, you need to download and install SLES12
   SDK first. you could download SLES12 SDK in here
   <ulink url="http://download.novell.com">http://download.novell.com</ulink>.
  </para>
  <para>
   After you download and install SLES12 SDK, We could use YMP file for OBS 1
   click install like openSUSE 13.1. Open your web browser and go to this URL
   <ulink url="http://download.opensuse.org/repositories/openSUSE:/Tools/SLE_11/OBS_Server.ymp">http://download.opensuse.org/repositories/openSUSE:/Tools/SLE_11/OBS_Server.ymp</ulink>.
  </para>
  <para>
   Like for openSUSE 11.3, I have referenced the previous from
   <ulink url="http://en.opensuse.org/openSUSE:Build_Service_Installation_SUSE">http://en.opensuse.org/openSUSE:Build_Service_Installation_SUSE</ulink>.
  </para>
  <para>
   After you clicked on that URL, you would see <guilabel>Opening
   OBS_Server.ymp</guilabel> window as described in the previous openSUSE 13.1
   section. Press <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button and
   <guibutton>Next</guibutton> button after YaST2 window pops up. If YaST lets
   you know successful install of OBS server, then you are ready to activate
   and run OBS on SLES12.
  </para>
  <para>
   To run OBS server on SLES12, you need to follow instructions based on
   /usr/share/doc/packages/obs-api/README.SETUP file as described in prior
   section. From here, you could refer to prior section for successful OBS run
   on your SLES12.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Installing a readymade OBS appliance in a VirtualBox</title>
  <para>
   This method is slightly less easy than the method using the readymade vmdk
   VMware disk, but it enables you to determine the size of your virtual disks
   to your convenience. It could also work with a real computer with two disks.
   It requires some knowledge of command line and partitioning.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Download the OBS appliance installer. Visit:
     <ulink url="http://www.openbuildservice.org/download">http://www.openbuildservice.org/download</ulink>
     and press the <guibutton>Download the OBS Appliance Installer</guibutton>
     button. It will start downloading an ISO image.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In VirtualBox, create a virtual machine with:
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        4 GB memory
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        1 virtual hard disk of 20 G for <filename>/</filename> and
        <filename>/var/cache/obs</filename>
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        1 virtual hard disk of 50 G for <filename>/srv/obs</filename>
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        a virtual CD-ROM driver pointing to the downloaded ISO image
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        network bridging with real Ethernet card
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Boot the virtual machine and choose to install the OBS server on the
     smaller virtual hard disk.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log into the virtual machine with Login: root and Password: opensuse. If
     needed, switch to German/French/whatever keyboard: <command># loadkeys
     de</command>. Inspect partitioning: <command># df -h</command>. It shows
     you that the root partition is small and already almost full (1.6 GB used
     out of 1.8). Let's prepare the other partitions to get a bit more working
     space. First, <command># fdisk /dev/sda</command> and prepare
     <filename>/dev/sda2</filename> to use the remaining space. Second,
     <command># fdisk /dev/sdb</command> and prepare
     <filename>/dev/sdb1</filename> to use all the space, with type 8e (Linux
     LVM):
<screen>
 # pvcreate /dev/sdb1
 # vgcreate OBS /dev/sdb1
 # lvcreate -n server -L 48G OBS
 # mkfs.ext4 /dev/OBS/server
</screen>
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Reboot, this time onto the hard disk. The CD-ROM might be disconnected, we
     will not need it anymore. Log in as root user, change keyboard if needed,
     and format <filename>/dev/sda2</filename>: <command># mkfs.ext4
     /dev/sda2</command>. Add following entry to /etc/fstab:
<screen>
/dev/sda2  /var/cache/obs  ext4  defaults  2 1
</screen>
     Mount the new partition: <command># mount /dev/sda2</command>. Get your IP
     address: <command># ifconfig</command>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>First steps with your new OBS server</title>
  <para>
   At this point, one of the methods above should have provided you with a
   running OBS instance. Let us get our first package building.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     From a web browser, access the web interface: https://vm.ip.address/.
     Accept the self-signed certificate.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the top right corner of the web interface, there is a <guibutton>Log
     In</guibutton> option. Use it to log in as: Admin opensuse.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click on the <guibutton>Configuration</guibutton> button to give your
     server a name and a description. Click on the
     <guibutton>Interconnect</guibutton> option. Choose
     <guilabel>openSUSE</guilabel> as the remote repository where we will pick
     up the packages of the build environment. Log out of the web interface.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Use <guibutton>Sign Up</guibutton> option to create a regular user account
     (for example: hmustermann).
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     As this normal user, click on the <guibutton>Home Project</guibutton>
     option and create your home project (that would be: "home:hmustermann").
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Go to this home project, and click on <guibutton>Create
     package</guibutton> to create your first package (let's say: "mypackage").
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Go back to your home project, and click the
     <guibutton>Repositories</guibutton> button. Choose to add a new repository
     and pick <guilabel>openSUSE 13.1</guilabel> (for example).
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Reboot the virtual machine to ensure all projects are rescanned.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     From outside the virtual machine and as a normal user, declare in
     <filename>~/.oscrc</filename> your new OBS user:
<screen>
[https://vm.ip.address]
user=hmustermann
pass=bond007
</screen>
     then checkout your new package: <command>$ osc -A https://vm.ip.address co
     home:hmustermann</command>. go to your first package: <command>$ cd
     home:hmustermann/mypackage</command>. and add some sources there (tarball,
     spec file, changelog, patches). Check them in, then trigger a remote
     build:
 <screen>
 $ osc add *
 $ osc commit
 $ osc rebuild
 </screen>
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     The built packages can be seen at: http://vm.ip.address:82/
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
</chapter>
