<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.1" xml:id="cha.obs.best-practices.bootstrapping"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" os="opensuse;novell">
 <title>Boot Strapping</title>
 <info/>
 <para> This chapter explains Boot strapping. In this chapter, You would learn
  how you could have other OBS projects and packages to your local OBS instance
  after your OBS install. There are some useful OSC commands examples and OBS
  working mechanism explanation in this chapter also. Basically this chapter is
  a copy from Build Service portal. For information about OBS bootstrapping on
  the Build Service portal, see <link
   xlink:href="https://en.opensuse.org/openSUSE:Build_Service_private_instance_boot_strapping"
  />. </para>
 <sect1>
  <title>The issue</title>
  <para> If you create a private instance of an OBS it is likely to be be fully
   independent. This means that your OBS needs to build its full reference
   tools chain. This process - called Bootstrap - presents the same problem as
   the Chicken and the Egg, which one came first ! In other words, you need to
   create a tool chain with the tool chain that you want to create. </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>A cheat sheet</title>
  <sect2>
   <title>Create your first project</title>
   <para> Log on to the Web API. The default user Admin, with the password
     <literal>opensuse</literal> is available. Create your own login and
    password and set yourself as Admin. Log on to the Web UI as Admin and click
    on the Icon "Configuration" and add the openSUSE Build Service as remote
    instance. Select from under <menuchoice>
     <guimenu>Locations</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Projects</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>. At the end of the list, click <guimenu>Add
    Project</guimenu>. Give it a name (e.g. Meego-test) Select your new project
    and create a sub-project 0.1. You have now a project Meego-test:1.0 Sub
    projects are handy to propagate Access Control Lists (acl) and for creating
    the version as a sub project simplifies the user and project
    administration. </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>Import your base Linux project</title>
   <para> We are now going to import the base project. I will describe two
    methods, one where you have a login on a remote OBS instance, one where you
    have only access to the rpm repository. In both cases you will need access
    to binary and source rpm. </para>
   <sect3>
    <title>With a login on a remote OBS</title>
    <para> The osc copypac (I assume that you have installed the osc package on
     your workstation) has an option -t which enables copying towards a remote
     target OBS instance. osc help and osc help command will advise on how to
     use these. First you need to import the project configuration. </para>
    <screen> 
$ export PROJECT=MeeGo-test:0.1
$ osc -A http://api-url-source-obs meta prjconf $PROJECT &gt; my_project.conf
$ osc -A http://api-url-target-obs meta prjconf -F my_project.conf $PROJECT
</screen>
    <para> Then import the project. As you might have some Links in the project
     that you import, it is a good idea to keep the source and target project
     names identical. </para>
    <screen> 
$ PRJ=ProjectToCopy; for i in `osc -A http://api.source.obs.domain ls $PRJ`; do \\
osc -A http://api.source.obs.domain \\
copypac -t http://api.target.obs.domain $PRJ $i $PRJ ;done 
</screen>
   </sect3>
   <sect3>
    <title>Without a Login on a remote OBS</title>
    <para> If you have access only to the repositories of your source reference
     target, then your life will be a bit more difficult. My advice would be to
     recheck if you find you cannot get a login on a public OBS service - such
     as provided by openSUSE or MeeGo - before proceeding this way. You will
     not be able to import the project config and you will have to create it by
     hand. This is too long to be covered in this HowTo. For more explanation
     about Build Service project config, see <link
      xlink:href="http://en.opensuse.org/openSUSE:Build_Service_prjconf"/>. </para>
    <para> Then you need to download all your rpm source on to a local machine
     and import it into your project with the command. </para>
    <screen><command>$ osc importsrcpkg</command></screen>
   </sect3>
   <sect3>
    <title>Bootstrapping</title>
    <para> To initiate the build process, we will copy the rpm binary from the
     source OBS of the source project. These binary rpms, from which we will
     remove any reference to release and version, will be used to trigger the
     first build. The OBS appliance will recompile all the rpms until all rpms
     in the project have been compiled only with packages compiled from their
     source code. Some base packages (e.g. tool chains) will be compiled
     several times during that process. Alternative You can build a first time
     against a target which is similar to the base that you need to boot strap
     in lieu of building against your own base and change the build reference
     to your bootstrap base once that the first build has been successful.
     Remember that you can also build against remote baseline. Double check
     that the preliminary step have been executed correctly. You must have
     already : copied a Linux base distribution in an OBS project defined a
     build target for that base project. </para>
    <para> If you have not defined a build target, the necessary directory
     structure will not exist. This is a mandatory step of preparation. Stop
     the scheduler as it will create a mess if the system is not stable: </para>
    <screen><command># rcobsscheduler stop</command></screen>
    <para> * Add binaries to the :full directory of the Project ssh onto the
     OBS server. Now go to the project’s build directory, and create a
     directory called “:full”. Note : standard is the default name of your
     Build repository as defined in your project. It might change depending of
     who created the initial build repo. </para>
    <screen><command># cd /obs/build/$PROJECT/standard/i586</command></screen>
    <para> This directory structure should already exist. If not, there is a
     problem (note that /obs is link and the target may vary with your
     implementation). Now create the “:full” directory. $ mkdir :full Copy over
     all the binary rpms of the project you are trying to build from scratch.
     These rpms should have the release and version numbers stripped from them.
     e.g. alsa-utils-1.0.22-2.7.i586.rpm -- should be – alsa-utils.rpm Note :
     If the original project has a :full directory you can copy from there to
     avoid the issue of stripping version and release numbers. * Add binaries
     to the :full directory of the Project. Change all user/group privileges
     under /srv/obs/build/ to “obsrun” </para>
    <screen><command># chown -R obsrun:obsrun /srv/obs/build</command></screen>
    <para> If you leave root as owner of :full, it will still build but the
     scheduler will fail (almost silently) to upgrade :full with the latest
     built packages. Except in very special cases, it is very unlikely that you
     want to do so. * Start the OBS scheduler </para>
    <screen><command># rcobsscheduler start</command></screen>
    <para> * Force the obs to reindex your new :full directory. It will send an
     event to the scheduler which will create a file named :full.solv </para>
    <screen> 
<command># obs_admin --rescan-repository $OBS-PROJECT $REPO $ARCH</command>
</screen>
    <sect4>
     <title>Troubleshooting</title>
     <para> At that time you should see your project restarting to build. If
      that would not be the case. * check that your files in your target :full
      directory are all own by the user obsrun. The following command should
      not return any file name. </para>
     <screen> 
#find /obs/build ! -user obsrun
#chown -R obsrun:obsrun  /obs/build   (will correct ownership issue)
</screen>
     <para> * Force the obs to reindex your new :full directory. It will create
      a file named :full.solv </para>
     <screen><command>$obs_admin --rescan-repository $OBS-PROJECT $REPO $ARCH</command></screen>
     <para> * Check that your rpm are valid (e.g. not damaged during transfer) </para>
     <screen> 
#cd /obs/build/$PROJECT/standard/i586:full
#for I in `ls *.rpm` ; do rpm -qlp $I &gt;/dev/null; if [ $? -ne 0 ] ;then echo $I &gt;&gt;../error.lst ; fi ; done
#cat ../error.lst (must be empty, all rpm in error needs re-installation) 
</screen>
     <para> * Still not working, get a look in the log files in the directory
      /obs/log. You can start by having a look at
      /obs/log/scheduler_TARGET_ARCH.log and search from the end for the string
      "expanding dependencies". You will find from there why the scheduler
      fails. </para>
     <screen><command>#tail -f /obs/log/scheduler_i586.log</command></screen>
    </sect4>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Creating a first project</title>
  <para> After creating a dedicated user via the Web API, log onto the Web UI
   again with your new login. Open your home project and create a sub project
   called "MyTest". To add a package in your new Home project, simply create a
   link [link Package from other Project] with one of the packages recently
   copied in your new OBS instance (see previous chapter Import your base
   project). Pick up a small one to speed compilation time. Click on the "+"
   near Build Repositories to add a repository. Move to the end of the page
   where all the standard Linux distributions are listed and click on
   [Advance]. Give a name to your repo, e.g. my-test and pick from the list the
   project/repo that you have just imported and rebuilt. This will request the
   OBS to build your new Home project against that repository. You can now
   check out your Home project with the osc command, modify a file or two and
   at your next check-in, the OBS will rebuild your Home project. If your
   reference project changes, the OBS will also rebuild your Home project.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
