<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC
  "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
 <chapter id="_troubleshooting">
  <title>Troubleshooting</title>
  <simpara>Here are two major classes of problems regarding the <emphasis role="strong">Open Build Service</emphasis></simpara>
  <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
   <listitem>
    <simpara>
Normal package build errors
</simpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <simpara>
Bugs, resource shortage or config issues caused issues
</simpara>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <simpara>The first category are errors like missing dependend packages in the build
environment, errors during compiling or linking, errors in the buid
description and so on. Most of them should not happen if the packager does
test the build locally before committing it to the OBS. This type of
problems is not covered by this chapter.</simpara>
  <section id="_general_hints">
   <title>General hints</title>
   <simpara>If you detect unexpected behavior of the open build service, you should
follow some rules to locate the problem:</simpara>
   <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
    <listitem>
     <simpara>
Consult the logfiles, for the backend look at <emphasis>/srv/obs/log</emphasis> for the
backend log files and <emphasis>/srv/www/obs/api/log</emphasis> for the frontend log files. See
the Log files <xref linkend="_log_files"/> for more details.
</simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>
Consult the normal OS system logs and the kernel log (dmesg) if here are
reported system or HW problems.
</simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>
Check if all services are running on the backend and frontend. See the
OBS Architecture <xref linkend="_obs_architecture"/> for details.
</simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>
Try to find an easy way to reproduce the problem.
</simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>
Look on <ulink url="https://github.com/openSUSE/open-build-service">https://github.com/openSUSE/open-build-service</ulink>
  if this issue was already reported.
</simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>
Use search machines (Google) to find out if others did also run into this problem. If you are lucky, you will find a fix or workaround as well.
</simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>
If you create a new bug report, include all information to reproduce the
problem and the complete error message/error log if here are any.
</simpara>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="_debug_frontend_problems">
   <title>Debug frontend problems</title>
   <simpara>If you get unexpected results from submitting comands with the <emphasis role="strong"><emphasis>osc</emphasis></emphasis> tool,
you can use the debug feature of the tools to get some more informations
what happen.</simpara>
   <simpara>osc debug options</simpara>
   <screen>     --debugger         jump into the debugger before executing anything
     --post-mortem      jump into the debugger in case of errors
     -t, --traceback    print call trace in case of errors
     -H, --http-debug   debug HTTP traffic (filters some headers)
     --http-full-debug  debug HTTP traffic (filters no headers)
     -d, --debug        print info useful for debugging</screen>
   <simpara>The <emphasis role="strong"><emphasis>--debugger</emphasis></emphasis> and <emphasis role="strong"><emphasis>--post-mortem</emphasis></emphasis> are only suitable for <emphasis>osc</emphasis>
developers. If you get a error message from osc the <emphasis role="strong"><emphasis>-t, --traceback</emphasis></emphasis> can
give the developer some more information about the problem. The <emphasis role="strong"><emphasis>-H, --http-debug</emphasis></emphasis> and
<emphasis role="strong"><emphasis>--http-full-debug</emphasis></emphasis> options are useful to see the raw answers of OBS API, often this gives a hint what maybe
wrong. If you report a problem regarding the <emphasis role="strong"><emphasis>osc</emphasis></emphasis> tool, it may help to include the osc output with
<emphasis role="strong">additional *<emphasis>--http-debug --traceback</emphasis></emphasis> options.</simpara>
   <warning>
    <simpara>With <emphasis role="strong"><emphasis>--http-full-debug</emphasis></emphasis> all http headers are included, this may include
user data and authentification stuff so review and replace such data with
XXXXXXXX or so before you post it on the internet.</simpara>
   </warning>
  </section>
 </chapter>
