<chapter version="5.1" xml:id="cha.obs.best-practices.basics"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" >
 <title>Basic Concepts and Work Styles</title>
 <info/>
 <para> These best practices should be known by every OBS user. They describe
  how to setup projects, working with own or foreign sources. </para>
 <sect1>
  <title>Setup a project re-using other projects binaries</title>
  <para>
   <xref linkend="obs.glos.project_binary"/> are the </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Setup a project reusing other projects sources</title>
  <para> You can also setup your own project using the sources, spec files and
   patches from another project and develop within this project.</para>
   <screen>#osc copypac SOURCEPRJ SOURCEPAC DESTPRJ</screen>
   <para>By default, Open Build Service will strip the maintainer info and now make
   it part of your own project. To clarify, when we speak of a project, it can
   mean just one package or a complete set of packages with their own build
   dependencies. </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Contribute Directly to External Projects</title>
  <para> In case a user does not have commit permissions for a project, they
   can request maintainership permissions for this project. This makes sense if
   the user is already known to the project owners and they trust him as a
   maintainer. There is a way to do this via the request system of OBS, but
   only via osc so far:</para>
   <screen># osc createrequest -a add_me maintainer PROJECT</screen>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Contribute Indirectly to Foreign Projects</title>
  <para> Users who are new to a given project, either because they are new
   users with Open Build Service or packaging or do not have any deeper
   knowledge about a certain project will not have direct commit permissions.
   However, they can still create a copy of any package source and ask back to
   merge their changes. Open Build Service has support to make this easy.
   <!-- TODO: merge collaboration wiki page here, when we have this docu online -->
  </para>
  <!-- this should become a standard style template and added to each section. -->
  <para> Wiki reference: <link
    xlink:href="http://en.opensuse.org/openSUSE:Build_Service_Collaboration"
    >User comment page</link>
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
