<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC
  "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.obs.build_containers">
 <title>Build Containers</title>
 <para>
  Containers are workloads which container all necessary files to make the workload
  independend of the running host OS. This includes (but is not limited to) libraries,
  executables and shared resource files.
 </para>
 <section>
   <title>Supported Containers</title>
   <para>
     A container that is providing it's own kernel is called virtual machine in this book.
     &OBS; supports container builds either by supporting the native build format or as
     side product of a different format. The range is from very simple chroot containers via 
     server format (eg Docker) or desktop format (eg. AppImage or Snap) up to full
     VM builds (OpenStack, kvm or LiveCD via kiwi).
    </para>
   <section>
     <title>SimpleImage</title>
     <para>
      SimpleImage is a special format which is using rpm spec file syntax and just packages
      the resulting install root as tar ball or squashfs image. The format is just using
      the BuildRequires tags inside of a file called "simpleimage", it supports also
      rpm macro handling to allow to define exceptions depending on the build environment.
     </para>
   </section>
   <section>
      <title>Docker</title>
      <para>
       Docker images are currently only supported via the kiwi tool.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>AppImage</title>
      <para>
       The Desktop orianted AppImage format is currently only formated as side effect of an rpm build. &OBS;
       supports signing and publishing the .AppImage files, the rest is handled via wrapper
       packages which converts a rpm (or deb package) into an AppImage file. 
       Own build rules can provided via a "Recipe" file, fallback code will be used if no 
       "Recipe" file is available.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Snap</title>
      <para>
       Snap format is supported natively. However, external resources are only supported 
       via source services and therefore not all build types are supported. Snapcraft 
       works also only with a ubuntu based base system (code for supporting rpm distros
       exists as well but got not merged upstream yet).
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Flatpack</title>
      <para>
        Flatpack is currently not supported due to the lacking ability of reproducable builds.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Livebuild</title>
      <para>
       Livebuild is the debian livebuild support for iso images.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Kiwi appliance formats</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Kiwi product builds</title>
      <para>
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
