<section id="concept_scm_integration">
 <title>Integrate External Source Repositories</title>
 <section>
  <title>Motivation</title>
  <para>
   This chapter makes some recommendations how upstream resources can be
   integrated into the build process. SCM stands for source control
   management. git, subversion or CVS are concrete implementations of a SCM.
   The OBS itself comes also with an own SCM, but this is only intended to
   manage the files needed for packaging. However, you can add references to
   external SCM systems. The source service system will mirror the sources
   and provide it to the build systems. OBS makes sure that you can access
   the sources of all builds also in the future, even when the upstream
   server delivers different or no content at all anymore. Using external
   SCM references have the following advantages
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <simpara>
        It is documented where a source comes from and how to create the archive.
      </simpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <simpara>
        Working on the upstream sources can be done directly in local checkouts and changes can be 
        tested via local builds before pushing to the SCM server.
      </simpara>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <simpara>
        The sources can be stored incremental and need less storage on the server.
      </simpara>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Creating a external SCM reference</title>
  <para>
   External refernces are defined in _service files. The file can look like
   this:
<screen>
<![CDATA[
<services>
  <service name="obs_scm">
    <param name="url">git://...</param>
    <param name="scm">git</param>
  </service>
  <service name="tar" mode="buildtime"/>
  <service name="recompress" mode="buildtime">
    <param name="file">*.tar</param>
    <param name="compression">xz</param>
  </service>
  <service name="set_version" mode="buildtime" />
</services>
      ]]>
</screen>
   The services are doing the following:
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>
      obs_scm: is mirroring the source. It is storing it as cpio archive, but for the build process this looks like a directory. It stores also additional information from the meta data to a file with obsinfo suffix.
    </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>
      tar: creates a tar ball from the directory
    </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>
      recompress: applies a compression on the tar ball
    </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>
      set_version: reads the version from the obsinfo file and adapts the build descriptions to it.
    </simpara>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   Please note that only the first service (obs_scm) is running on the OBS
   server. The other services are running during the build process. They can
   also be replaced by any user by providing alternative implementations of
   them or writing their own service from scratch.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Working with local checkouts</title>
  <para>
   Using
<screen>
            osc build
          </screen>
   in any package with such a defintion will do the same process local. The
   only difference is that you get a local subdirectory with the SCM
   content. You can go inside and work as you are used to. Any changes
   inside will be used for your next local build. No matter if they got
   pushed to the upstream server or not. However, you need to push it to
   upstream when you let the OBS server re-fetch the changes from upstream.
   The only way out would be to set the "obs_scm" service to mode disabled
   and upload your local archive.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Manage your build description in SCM</title>
  <para>
   The "obs_scm" service allows you to export files next to the archive. You
   can specify one or more files using the "extract" parameter. Use it for
   your build description files.
  </para>
 </section>
</section>
