<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC
  "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.obs.best-practices.basics">
 <title>Basic Concepts and Work Styles</title>
 <para>
  These best practices should be known by every OBS user. They describe how
  to setup projects, working with own or foreign sources.
 </para>
 <section>
  <title>Setup a project re-using other projects binaries</title>
  <para>
   <xref linkend="obs.glos.project_binaries"/> are the
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Setup a project reusing other projects sources</title>
  <para>
   You can also setup your own project using the sources, spec files and
   patches from another project and develop within this project.
<screen><command>#osc copypac SOURCEPRJ SOURCEPAC DESTPRJ  </command></screen>
   By default, &obs; will strip the maintainer info and now make it part of
   your own project. To clarify, when we speak of a project, it can mean
   just one package or a complete set of packages with their own build
   dependencies.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Contribute Directly to External Projects</title>
  <para>
   In case a user does not have commit permissions to a project, he can
   request maintainership permissions for this project. This makes sense if
   the user is already known to the project owners and they trust him as a
   maintainer. There is a way to do this via the request system of OBS, but
   only via osc so far:
<screen><command># osc createrequest -a add_me maintainer PROJECT</command></screen>
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Contribute Indirectly to Foreign Projects</title>
  <para>
   Users who are new to a given project, either because they are new users
   with &obs; or packaging or don't have any deeper knowledge about a
   certain project won't have direct commit permissions. However, they can
   still create a copy of any package source and ask back to merge their
   changes. &obs; has support to make this easy.
<!-- TODO: merge collaboration wiki page here, when we have this docu online -->
  </para>
<!-- this should become a standard style template and added to each section. -->
  <para>
   Wiki reference:
   <ulink url="http://en.opensuse.org/openSUSE:Build_Service_Collaboration">User
   comment page</ulink>
  </para>
 </section>
</chapter>
