<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC
  "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<!-- note: this is just a collection file atm, bigger parts should be moved to own files & chapters -->
<chapter id="cha.obs.concepts">
 <title>OBS Concepts</title>
 <para>
  We describe here the high level concepts how &obs; is designed, manages it's
  content and is supposed to work.
 </para>
 <section>
  <title>Project organization</title>
  <para>
   All sources and binaries which are hosted inside of OBS are organized in
   projects. A project is the container defining a larger task. It defines who
   is working there
  </para>
  <section>
   <title>Project meta data</title>
   <para>
    A project gets configured in the project
    <command>/source/$PROJECT/_meta</command> path. It can be edited in web
    interface in the <command>RAW Config</command> tab or via command line via
<screen><command>osc meta prj -e $PROJECT</command></screen>
    This file contains
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>
                 generic description data in <command>title</command> and <command>description</command> elements.
              </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>
                 An ACL list of users and groups connected with a role. The <command>maintainer</command>
                 role defines the list of users permitted to commit changes to the project.
              </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>
                 A number of flags, controlling the build and publishing process and possible read
                 access protections. 
              </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara>
                 A list of repositories to be created. This list defines what other repositories
                 should be used, which architectures shall be built and build job scheduling parameters.
              </simpara>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    The following flags can be used to control the behavior of a package or
    project. Most of them can also be limited to specified repositories or
    architectures.
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <simpara><command>build</command> flag defines if package sources should get build. If enabled, it signals the scheduler
            to trigger server side builds based on events like source changes, changes of packages used in
            the build environment or manual rebuild triggers. A local build via CLI is possible independent of 
            this flag.
            Default is enabled.
              </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara><command>publish</command> can be used to enable or disable publishing the build result as repository. This happens
            after an entire repository has finished build for an architecture. A publish also gets triggered, when
            the publish flag is enabled after a repository finished the build.
            Default is enabled.
              </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara><command>debuginfo</command> can be used to modify the build process to create debuginfo data along with the package
            build for later debugging purposes. A flag change is not triggering rebuilds, it just affects the next build.
            Default is disabled.
              </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara><command>useforbuild</command> is used to control if a built result shall be copied to the build pool. This means it
            will get used for other builds in their buildenvironment. When this is disabled, the build has no
            influence on builds of other packages using this repository. In case a former build exists the old
            binaries will be used. Disabling this flag also means that "wipe" commands to remove binary files
            will have no effect on the build pool.
            A flag change is not triggering rebuilds, it just affects the next build.
            Default is enabled.
              </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara><command>access</command> flag can be used to hide an entire project. This includes binaries
            and sources. It can only be used at project creation time and can just be
            enabled (making it public again) afterwards.
             This flag can only be used on projects.
            Default is enabled.
              </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara><command>sourceaccess</command> flag can be used to hide the sources, but still show the existence of a
            project or package. This also includes debug packages in case the distribution is supporting this correctly.
              This flag can only be used at package creation time. There is no code
            yet which is checking for possible references to this package.
            Default is enabled.
              </simpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <simpara><command>downloadbinary</command> permission still exists like before. However, unlike "access"
            and "sourceaccess" this is not a security feature. It is just a convenience feature, which
            makes it impossible to get the binaries via the API directly. But it is still possible
            to get the binaries via build time in any case.
            Default is enabled.
              </simpara>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Project build configuration.</title>
   <para>
    A project gets configured in the project
    <command>/source/$PROJECT/_config</command> path. It can be edited in web
    interface in the <command>Project Config</command> tab or via one of the
    following command lines
<screen><command>osc meta prjconf -e $PROJECT</command>
<command>osc co $PROJECT _project</command></screen>
    This file contains information on how to setup a build environment.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Project build macro configuration</title>
   <para>
    The macro configuration is part of the build configuration in
    <command>/source/$PROJECT/_config</command>. It can be added at the end
    behind a <command>Macro:</command>
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>An OBS Package</title>
   <para>
    An OBS Package is a sub name space below a project. It contains the
    specification of a single package build for all specified repositories.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>The API</title>
  <para>
   ...
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>The OBS Interconnect</title>
  <para>
   The OBS interconnect is a mechanism to connect two OBS instances. All
   content, including sources and binary build results will be available in the
   connecting instance. Unlike other methods the instances will also notify
   each other about changes.
<!--
 * xml example to setup
 * webui interconnect page
 * example to use sources from remote
 * example to use remote repos
 * default distro list functionality
 * limitations (chainig, submitting back, read access control)
-->
  </para>
 </section>
 <xi:include href="obs_concepts_dod.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
 <xi:include href="obs_concepts_scm.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
 <section>
  <title>Attribute System</title>
  <para>
   ...
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Automatic source processing</title>
  <para>
   ...
  </para>
 </section>
</chapter>
