<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.1" xml:id="cha-obs-qa-hooks"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" >
 <title>Quality Assurance(QA) Hooks</title>
 <info/>
 <para> OBS provides multiple hooks to place automated or manual tests at
  different points of time. </para>
 <para> This chapter describes the different possibilities to provide and
  execute QA checks. The order of the items is sorted by the order in a typical
  development process. It is preferred to add a check as early as possible in
  the process to keep turn-around times small. </para>
 <sect1>
  <title>Source Related Checks</title>
  <para> Things which can be verified based on a given source can be checked
   even before commit time on the developers workstation. This is the earliest
   possible point of time to add a check. But it can also optionally be
   enforced on the server side. </para>
  <para> Automated source processing is done by source services in OBS world.
   Check the source service chapter how to use or write one. It is important to
   decide if the test case shall output warning messages and when it shall
   report an error by exit status. </para>
  <para> Test cases in source services get usually applied to all packages of a
   project. (It is possible to execute it only for specific packages though.)
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Build Time Checks</title>
  <sect2>
   <title>In-Package Checks</title>
   <para> Checks running during the build of a package are usually test cases
    provided by the author of a package. However, the packager can also add
    simple checks, for example, for code that is known to break on version updates
    and might be forgotten when the package is touched the next
    time. </para>
   <para> These test are often specific for a concrete package only. So it is
    typically executed in %check section of rpm spec files directly. In case
    the check can be used with multiple package source, it is a good idea to
    package the test case in an own package and just call it from the other
    packages. </para>
   <para> rpm calls %check after %install section and before creating the
    actual checks. </para>
   <para>
    &suse; distributions also provide build time checks to test the
    installed files inside of the build root. It is to be used for test cases
    which shall run on all packages which are built inside of a distribution.
    This hook can be used by installing a file to /usr/lib/rpm/brp-suse.d/
    directory. These scripts also have the power to modify installed files
    if needed. </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>Post Build Checks</title>
   <para>
    The standard tool to test binary packages for &rpmf;-based distributions
    is <command>rpmlint</command>. &debf;-based distributions use the
    <command>lintian</command> tool instead.
   </para>
   <para> These checks are executed by the build script after a successful
    build. Note that these are executed as the standard user by default.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>Post Build Root Checks</title>
   <para> Files in /usr/lib/build/checks/* are executed as root user. Typical
    use cases are install tests of the build packages to ensure that the
    scripts inside of the packages are working in general. </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>&kiwi; Specific Post Build Root Checks</title>
   <para> The file /usr/lib/build/kiwi_post_run is executed after &kiwi; jobs
    have finished. It can be used to run the appliance or to modify it. For
    example to package an appliance into an rpm. </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Workflow Checks</title>
  <para> Workflow steps, for example transferring packages from one project to
   another, are done via requests in OBS. At least when multiple parties are
   involved. One or more of these parties can be automated test cases. Or human
   manual approval steps. </para>
  <para> Default reviews can be defined inside of projects and packages. A new
   request to a certain package does get the reviewers added defined in target
   projects and packages. Reviewers can be currently users, groups or the
   maintainers of a specified project or package. </para>
  <sect2>
   <title>Automated Test Cases</title>
   <para> Open requests can be requested in an XML parseable way via the API
    running </para>
   <screen><command>osc api /request?states=review&amp;user=auto-review-user&amp;roles=reviewer&amp;reviewstates=new&amp;view=collection</command></screen>
   <para>
    &osccmd; can be used to accept or decline requests
    after running the automated test. It can also add a review comment which you can use to give a reason (for example, error messages) for accepting or declining a request.
    Requests, which are not
    tested, for example because they are of a not matching type (for example, deleting
    packages) needs to get also a review accept. Otherwise, this would block the process. </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
