<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter version="5.1" xml:id="cha-obs-build-containers"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" >
 <title>Build Containers</title>
 <info>
  <abstract>
   <para/>
  </abstract>
 </info>
 <para>
  Containers are workloads which embed all necessary files to make the workload
  independent of the running host OS. This includes (but is not limited to)
  libraries, executables and shared resource files.
 </para>

 <sect1 xml:id="supported-formats">
  <title>Supported Container Formats</title>

  <para>
   A container that is providing its own kernel is commonly called a virtual
   machine and will be referred to as such in this book. The Open Build Service
   (OBS) supports container builds either by supporting the native build format
   or as side product of a different format. This ranges is from very simple
   chroot containers over server (for example, Docker) or desktop formats (for
   example, AppImages, Snaps or Flatpaks) up to full VM builds (such as for
   OpenStack, KVM, or as a Live CD via &kiwi;).
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>SimpleImage</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      SimpleImage is a special format which uses the rpm spec file syntax and
      just packages the resulting install root as tar ball or squashfs image.
      The format is just using the BuildRequires tags from a file called
      <filename>simpleimage</filename>, it supports also rpm macro handling to
      allow for exceptions depending on the build environment.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Docker</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Docker images can be built either via the &kiwi; tool or from
      Dockerfile build descriptions.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>AppImage</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The desktop-oriented AppImage format is currently only created as a side
      effect of an RPM build. Open Build Service (OBS) supports signing and
      publishing the .AppImage files, the rest is handled via wrapper packages
      which converts an RPM (or DEB package) into an AppImage file. Own build
      rules can provided via a <filename>Recipe</filename> file, fallback code
      will be used if no <filename>Recipe</filename> file is available.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Snap</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The Snap format is supported natively. However, external resources are
      only supported via source services and therefore not all build types are
      supported. Snapcraft only works with Ubuntu-based base systems. (Code to
      support &rpmf;-based distributions exists as well but has not been merged
      upstream yet.)
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Flatpak</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Flatpak packages can be built in the Open Build Service, see
      <xref linkend="sec-pkgfmt-flatpak"/> for further details.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Livebuild</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Livebuild is the Debian livebuild support for ISO images.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Mkosi</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/systemd/mkosi/">Mkosi</link> allows
      building images for rpm, arch, deb, and gentoo based distributions, see
      <xref linkend="sec-pkgfmt-mkosi"/> for further details.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <!--  <sect2>
   <title>&kiwi; Appliance Formats</title>
   <para> </para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2>
   <title>&kiwi; Product Builds</title>
   <para> </para>
   </sect2>-->
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="container-registry">
  <title>Container Registry</title>

  <para>
   Container Registries are repositories that container images are published
   and can be automatically pulled from using tools like
   <link xlink:href="https://podman.io/">podman</link> or
   <link xlink:href="https://www.docker.com/">docker</link>.
  </para>

  <para>
   The Open Build Service will automatically publish container images in a
   OCI-compatible registry, with the URLs to the images constructed as follows:
   <literal> $BASE/$PROJECT/$REPOSITORY/$IMAGE_NAME:$TAG </literal> with the
   following components:
  </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>$BASE</literal>: URL/IP under which the Open Build Service
      instance is reachable
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>$PROJECT</literal>: The name of the project where the image is
      build, with all colons replaced with forward slashes.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>$REPOSITORY</literal>: The name of the repository where the
      containers are published.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>$IMAGE_NAME</literal>: The name of this container image. It
      defaults to the name of the package from which the container is build.
      Alternatively, a different image name can be specified in the build
      recipe, e.g. via the <literal>containerconfig</literal> element in a
      &kiwi; file (see
      <link xlink:href="https://osinside.github.io/kiwi/building_images/build_container_image.html?highlight=containerconfig">the
      kiwi documentation</link> for further details).
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>$TAG</literal>: The image tag. This defaults to
      <literal>latest</literal> with alternatives being provided in a similar
      fashion as the image's name.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>


  <para>
   The
   <link
     xlink:href="https://github.com/openSUSE/cooverview">cooverview</link>
   project provides a simple user-facing webpage to search for containers
   published by the Open Build Service and can be used to conveniently obtain
   the correct registry URLs. It is used to power
   <link
     xlink:href="https://registry.opensuse.org/">registry.opensuse.org</link>
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="image-signatures">
  <title>Container Image Signatures</title>

  <para>
   The &obs; automatically signs every package that has been build and
   publishes the cryptographic signature alongside with it. Container images
   are no exception to this and the detached signatures can be used by
   <link xlink:href="https://podman.io/">podman</link> to verify every image
   that is pulled from the registry.
  </para>

  <para>
   Podman has to be configured first as outlined in the following steps.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Create a <literal>yaml</literal> file under
     <literal>/etc/containers/registries.d/</literal> with an appropriate name
     for your instance and the following contents:
    </para>
     <example>
      <title>registry.yaml</title>
<screen>
---
docker:
  <replaceable>REGISTRY_URL</replaceable>:
    sigstore: <replaceable>REGISTRY_URL</replaceable>/sigstore
</screen>
     </example>
     <para>
     Replace <replaceable>REGISTRY_URL</replaceable> with the appropriate URL
     to your instance of &obs; (for example,
     <literal>registry.opensuse.org</literal>).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Add the following object into the key <literal>transports</literal> in the
     file <filename>/etc/containers/policy.json</filename>:
    </para>
    <example>
     <title>policy.json</title>
<screen>
    "docker": {
      "<replaceable>REGISTRY_URL</replaceable>": [
        {
          "type": "signedBy",
          "keyType": "GPGKeys",
          "keyPath": "<replaceable>PATH_TO_PUBLIC_KEY</replaceable>"
        }
      ]
    }
</screen>
    </example>
    <para>
     The complete <filename>/etc/containers/policy.json</filename> can then
     look like this:
    </para>
    <example>
     <title>policy.json</title>
<screen>
{
  "default": [
    {
      "type": "insecureAcceptAnything"
    }
  ],
  "transports": {
    "docker-daemon": {
      "": [
        {
          "type": "insecureAcceptAnything"
        }
      ]
    },
    "docker": {
      "<replaceable>REGISTRY_URL</replaceable>": [
        {
          "type": "signedBy",
          "keyType": "GPGKeys",
          "keyPath": "<replaceable>PATH_TO_PUBLIC_KEY</replaceable>"
        }
      ]
    }
  }
}
</screen>
    </example>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Save the public key of the project where your image is build under
     <replaceable>PATH_TO_PUBLIC_KEY</replaceable> (you can choose any location
     to which you have read access, only ensure that you specify it in
     <filename>/etc/containers/policy.json</filename> as well).
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   Podman will from now on automatically fetch the published signatures from
   the backend and verify them before storing the images locally.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
