<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC
  "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.obs.build_process">
 <title>Build Process</title>
 <para>
  Each package build is done in a fresh environment. This is done to ensure
  that no dependencies are missing and every later build produces identical
  results.
 </para>
 <section>
  <title>How is a build process defined</title>
  <para>
   ...
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>How does a build process work</title>
  <para>
   All sources and binaries which are hosted inside of OBS are organized in
   projects. Projects do host in sources inside of package containers again.
   The sources get build according to the repository configuration inside of
   the project.
  </para>
  <section>
   <title>Preinstall phase</title>
   <para>
    The step of this phase depends on the type of the buildroot (building
    environment). OBS supports three different types buildroot:
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <simpara>
         chroot
       </simpara>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <simpara>
         XEN
       </simpara>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <simpara>
         KVM
       </simpara>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    In the preinstall phase, the OBS Worker creates a small base system (chroot
    or VM Image) with manually extracted packages (file system, coreutils,
    binutils, rpm/debutils, etc.), copies all necessary build requirements
    into the base system.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Install Phase</title>
   <para>
    Depending of the chosen build root the worker starts the XEN/KVM virtual
    machine or enters the build root. If this was successful the install
    phase reinstalls all base package from above and additionally all packages
    you have defined in your package recipe. After this phase the environment is
    ready to process the recipe.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Package build</title>
   <para>
    Regarding the package type the buildroot executes different build commands.
    On RPM-based distributions it is called "rpmbuild". On Debian-based distributions, it is
    "dpkg-buildpackage" and on Arch Linux you use "pacman". Now everything
    depends on the quality and the type of your build recipe. In most cases the
    source code will be compiled now and get packed into the specific package
    format. On RPM based distributions there are additional security and
    cleanness checks called rpmlint, which have the goal to improve the quality
    of the packages.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Post build steps</title>
   <para>
    The generated packages are taken from the Worker get signed by the OBS
    Signer and are published to the Repository.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Different ways to build</title>
  <para>
   ...
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Security aspects</title>
  <para>
   ...
  </para>
 </section>
</chapter>
