<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC
  "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>

<chapter id="cha.obs.maintenance_setup">
  <title>The Maintenance Support</title>
  <para>This chapter explains the setup and workflow of doing maintenance the openSUSE way. 
        However, this should not be limited to openSUSE distribution projects but be usable anywhere (including
        all steps or in parts).
        </para>

  <para>The goal of the OBS maintenance process is to publish updates for a frozen project, in
        this example an entire distribution. These updates need to be approved by a maintenance 
        team and the published result must contain documentation about the changes and be applicable
	in the easiest way by the users. The result is a package repository with additional informations
	about the solved problems and defined groups of packages to achieve that. Also binary delta data
        may get generated to reduce the needed download size for the clients.</para>
  
  <section>
    <title>Simple Project Setup</title>
    <figure>
      <title>Simple Project Setup</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="maintenance_project_setup.png" width="800" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>This figure is giving a basic overview about the project setup and general workflow for a single
          package and single maintained distribution. It shows the "openSUSE:11.4" project, which is considered to be frozen and not changing
          at all anymore. The "openSUSE:11.4:Update" projects hosts all officially released updates. It does not build
          any binary, just gets it sources and binaries from the maintenance incident project via the release process. The
          incident project is named "openSUSE:Maintenance:IDxxx" in this example, which is under control of the maintenance team.
          Official updates get built and reviewed here. QA teams are also
          testing the binaries from here. However, a user can prepare it in the same way in his project and start the 
          maintenance process via doing a "maintenance" request.</para>
   <itemizedlist>
     <listitem><simpara>
     openSUSE:11.4 is the <xref linkend="obs.glos.ga_project"/> in this example. Frozen and not changing anymore.
     </simpara></listitem>
     <listitem><simpara>
     openSUSE:11.4:Update is the <xref linkend="obs.glos.update_project"/> to release official updates.
     </simpara></listitem>
     <listitem><simpara>
     openSUSE:Maintenance is the <xref linkend="obs.glos.maintenance_project"/>.
     </simpara></listitem>
     <listitem><simpara>
     openSUSE:Maintenance:IDxxx is the <xref linkend="obs.glos.incident"/> project.
     </simpara></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How to use the maintenance process</title>
    <para>This describes all required steps by all involved persons from preparing to releasing a maintenance update.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Way A: Process gets initiated by the maintainer</title>
      <para>A user is usually starting to prepare an update by creating a maintenance branch. This is typically done by
            creating an own maintenance project. Usually multiple released products are affected, so the server can find
            out which one are maintained by a given source package name, in this example for glibc including checkout via</para>
      <screen><command>osc mbranch -c glibc</command></screen>
      <para>This is equivalent to the api call <command>/source?cmd=branch&amp;package=glibc</command>.</para>
      <para>It is also possible to branch only one defined version, if it is known that only one version is affected. In this
            example the openSUSE:12.1 version:</para>
      <screen><command>osc branch -c openSUSE:12.1 glibc</command></screen>
      <para>The user needs to do the needed modifications now. Packages will be built and can be tested. Afterwards he
            need to add information about the purpose of this maintenance update via</para>
      <screen><command>osc patchinfo</command></screen>
      <para>If the source changes contain references to bugzilla or CVE issue trackers these will be used by default</para>
      <para>The server will create a full maintenance channel now, in case the user wants to test this as well. Otherwise
            he can create a maintenance request:</para>
      <screen><command>osc maintenancerequest</command></screen>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Way B: Process gets initiated by the maintenance team</title>
      <para>The maintenance team may start the process (for example because a security issue was reported and the
            maintenance team decided that a fix is required). In this case the incident gets created via the webui or via
            the api call</para>
      <para><command>osc createincidient [PROJECT]</command></para>
      <para><command>osc api /source/PROJECT?cmd=createmaintenanceincident</command></para>
      <para><command>osc api /source?cmd=createmaintenanceincident&amp;attribute=OBS:Maintenance</command>.</para>
      <para>Right now the developer must be notified outside of OBS about the expected work (eg. via bugzilla). In future we
            may add a pull request here to have one place for the "my work" overview.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Maintenance Incident Processing</title>
      <para>The maintenance incidents are usually managed by a maintenance team. In case the incident got started by a 
	    maintainer a maintenance request is targeted towards the defined maintenance project, in our example this
	    is openSUSE:Maintenance. 
            The defined maintainer and reviewers in this project need to decide about this request. In case it gets
            accepted, the server is creating a subproject with a unique incident ID and copies the sources and build settings to it.
	    The origin project will get removed usually via the cleanup option. This maintenance project is used to build the
	    final packages. The
	    maintenance team may still modify them or the patchinfo data at this point. An outside maintainer can still submit
	    changes via standard submit request mechanism, but direct write permissions are not granted.
	    When the maintenance people are satisfied
            with the update, they can create a request to release the sources and binaries to the final openSUSE:11.4:Update
            project.</para>
      <screen><command>osc releaserequest</command></screen>
      <para>The release request needs to specify the source and target for each package. In case just the source package or 
            project is specified the api is completing the request on creation time. It is using this based on the source link
            target of each package and the release information in the repository definitions.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Incident gets released</title>
      <para>The release process gets usually started via creating a release request. This sets all affected packages to the
            locked state, which means that all commands for editing the source or triggering rebuilds are not allowed anymore.
            </para>
      <para>The release request typically needs to be approved by QA and other teams as defined in the Update project. In case 
            something gets declined, the necessary changes need to be submitted to the maintenance project and a new release request
            has to be created.</para>
      <para>A unique release ID will be generated and become part of the updateinfo.xml file in the target project on release event.
            This ID is different from the incident ID and is usually in the style of "YEAR-COUNTER". The counter is strictly increasing
            on each release. In case of a re-release of the same incident a release counter will be added.</para>
      <para> A different naming scheme
            can be defined via the OBS:MaintenanceIdTemplate attribute value. The release will move all packages to the update
            project and extend the target package name with the incident ID. Binaries will be moved as well without modification.
            The exception is the updateinfo.xml which will be modified by replacing its incident id with the release id.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Incident gets reopened and re-released</title>
      <para>An update should not, but may have an undetected regression. In this case the update needs a re-release. (If another problem
            shall be fixed a new incident should be created instead.)</para>
      <para>If the current update harms the systems, the maintenance team may decide to take it back immediatly. It can be done by removing the
            patchinfo.ID package container in the Update projects. This will create a new update channel without this update.</para>
      <para>To re-open a release incident project, the release target trigger needs to be set back to <command>trigger=maintenance</command>.
            This can be done via editing the meta data. The incident project gets listed as running in the webui now.</para>
      <para>To be able to do rebuilds or source changes (eg. via accepting submit requests) the packages need to be un-locked.
            can be defined via the OBS:MaintenanceIdTemplate attribute value. The release will move all packages to the update
            project and extend the target package name with the incident ID. Binaries will be moved as well without modification.
            The exception is the updateinfo.xml which will be modified by replacing its incident id with the release id.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
   
  <section>
    <title>OBS Internal Mechanisms</title>
    <para>OBS is tracking maintenance work and can be used as a database for future and past updates.</para>
    <section>
      <title>The workflow step by step</title>
      <para>A maintenance incident is started by creating the incident project, either via a developer request
            or by the maintenance team.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><simpara>
            Incident project container is created. This is always a sub project to the maintenance
            project. A unique ID (counter) is used as subproject name. Build is disabled by default project wide.
        </simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          Default content for an incident is added via branch by attribute call:
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><simpara>
                Package sources get added based on given package and attribute name from all existing project instances. 
                The package name is extended by the source project name to allow multiple instances of same package in one project.
                Source revision links are using the xsrcmd5 to avoid that other
                releases will affect this package instance. TBD: how to raise the source revision to current version manually ?
            </simpara></listitem>
            <listitem><simpara>
                Build repositories are added if missing. All repositories from all projects where the package sources gets branched
                from are used. The build flags in the package instances gets switched on for these.
            </simpara></listitem>
            <listitem><simpara>
                A release target definition is added to the repository configuration via additional releasetarget element. The special
                release condition "maintenance" gets defined for this.
            </simpara></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara>
            Fixes for the packages need to get submitted now. <!-- point to pull request -->
        </simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara>
            A patchinfo file need to get added describing the issue. 
        </simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara>
            OBS server is building packages according to the sources and update information according to the patchinfo data.
        </simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara>
            one or more release requests get created. It does also set the project to "freeze" state by default, this means no source 
            changes are possible anymore and all running builds get canceled.
        </simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara>
            Usually the request is in review state with defined reviewers from the release project. All reviewers need to review
            the state in the incident project.
        </simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara>
            Request changes into state "new" when all reviewers accepted the release request.
        </simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            The release happens on accepting the request by the maintainers of the release project.
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><simpara>
            All package sources and binaries get copied into a package container where the package name gets extended by the incident number.
            </simpara></listitem>
            <listitem><simpara>
            A main package gets created or updated, it just contains a link to the current incident package. Eg glibc points to glibc.42. The
            purpose of this main package is to have a place to refer to the current sources of a package.
            </simpara></listitem>
            <listitem><simpara>
            The release target condition=maintenance gets removed.
            </simpara></listitem>
            <listitem><simpara>
            The updateinfo.xml gets updated with the existing or now created unique updateinfo ID.
            </simpara></listitem>
            <listitem><simpara>
            The server will update the repository based on all existing binaries.
            </simpara></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara>
            OPTIONAL: A maintenance coordinator may remove the release by removing the package instances inside the release project. The source
            link has to be fixed manually. (We may offer a function for this).
        </simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            OPTIONAL: A maintenance incident can be restarted by 
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><simpara>
            Removing the lock flag.
            </simpara></listitem>
            <listitem><simpara>
            Adding again the condition=maintenance attribute to the release target which requires a re-release.
            </simpara></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para> NOTE: The step 1 and 2 may be done via accepting an incident request instead.
            </para>
    </section>


    <section>
      <title>Search for incidents</title>
      <para>The webui shows the running and past incidents when going to the maintenance project (openSUSE:Maintenance
            in our example). It shows the open requests either for creating or release an incident. Also the open incidents,
            which are not yet released are visible.</para>
      <para>The following items list some common ways to search for maintenance incidents via the api:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
<!--
        <listitem><para>
          A developer can see the work to be done by him via searching for open pull requests.
          <screen><command> TBD. </command></screen>
        </para></listitem>
-->
        <listitem><para>
          A maintenance coordinator can see requests for doing a maintenance release via searching for open requests with maintenance_incident action 
          against the maintenance project. API call example:
          <screen><command>/search/request?match=(state/@name='new') and action/@type='maintenance_incident' and action/target/@project='openSUSE:Maintenance')</command></screen>
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          A maintenance coordinator can see open incidents via searching for incidents project repositories which have a release
          target with maintenance trigger. Note: this search result is showing all repositories of a matching project.
          <screen><command>/search/project?match=(repository/releasetarget/@trigger=maintenance)</command></screen>
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          A maintenance coordinator can see updates which currently are reviewed (for example by a QA team) via
          <screen><command>/search/request?match=(state/@name='review') and action/@type='maintenance_release')</command></screen>
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
          A maintenance coordinator can see updates ready to release via searching for open requests with maintenance_release action.
          <screen><command>/search/request?match=(state/@name='new') and action/@type='maintenance_release')</command></screen>
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How to setup projects for doing a maintenance cycle</title>
    <section>
      <title>Defining a maintenance space</title>
      <para>An OBS server is using by default a maintenance space defined via the OBS:Maintenance attribute. This must get created
            on a project where maintenance incident projects should get created below. This project is also defining the default
            maintenance maintainers and reviewers in it's acl list.</para>
      <para>It is possible to have multiple and independent maintenance name spaces, however the maintenance request must be created
            against this other namespace manually or using a different attribute. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Maintained Project Setups</title>
      <para>Maintained projects must be frozen, this means no changes in sources or binaries. All updates will be hosted in the defined
            update project. This project gets defined via the OBS:UpdateProject attribute which must contain a value with the
            update project name. In addition to this, an attribute to define the active maintenance should also be defined, by default
            the OBS:Maintained attribute. The osc mbranch command will take packages from this project as a result. </para>
      <para>The Update project should be defined as build disabled as well. Also define a project link to the main project and at least 
            one repository building against the main project.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

</chapter>
